i am recording on the computer i have
two backup recordings going this time
and i have optimized my podcast
recording situation for dog comfort
excellent because lucy is here
and she refused to sleep in her basket
instead she wants to sleep on my lap
while i'm recording the podcast
so i had to change the whole setup you
frequently change yourself
dogs come first
it feels like it has been a really
really long time
since we've recorded a show the way
we're recording a show today like
honestly like it feels like it wasn't
even the same show that used to do what
we're doing today i know exactly what
you're saying
it's like oh mike
i talked to him
a lifetime ago
it's it's amazing well okay we have that
which is like it just feels like it's
been forever since we recorded an
episode but i mean more that you're not
at home i'm
in a whole different country i'm in
america at my parents house am i a whole
new person because it feels like the
person i used to be
he only existed in one location he never
went anywhere but the person i am now
the whole world is available he can go
places
he can see things
he can do things what a what a novel
concept
the previous person doing things no
there was there was no doing things
there was
staying at home
so yeah it it does feel like
wow it sure has been a real thing since
the last time we spoke to each other so
in our last episode we were wondering if
you were going to be able to make
your various trips and it seems like
that you
obviously have done it because you are
in america now you're with your parents
uh how was your travel experience
yeah it's it's one of these funny things
where
uh i know that
previous me was quite concerned
i don't i don't i
i think we talked about like betting on
if i was going to be able to do all of
my travel plans successfully and i think
i gave it like 50 50 odds i don't
remember because you were adding the
complexity in right because you were
going from home and then you're going
somewhere in europe and then you're
going back home again and then to
america did you end up doing that by the
way because i remember there was a
conversation of whether you would just
leave from location one did you go home
again and leave yeah so the plan was
from to go from london to switzerland
and then from switzerland to north
carolina
but i was very concerned that travel
complexities wouldn't allow that to
happen
but from current me's perspective it's a
little bit like oh what was that guy
worried about nothing was a problem like
ev everything was really easy and it's
like okay it's travel the way travel is
the way i remember travel there's just
one additional piece of paper that you
need to get and that's your coveted test
results and i had my test done they both
came through just fine and
at heathrow airport they were very
concerned to look and check and scan the
piece of paper and then they let me
through and it was totally fine and at
zurich airport literally no one ever
looked at the test results i never
showed that document to anyone and i
just flew to america so
uh no problems whatsoever on the flying
front oh so you did go from zurich to
north carolina that was the final plan
okay that did happen and the funny thing
was no one checked the paperwork i
almost felt like i wanted to show the
flight attendant on that flight like oh
look at me i have a test result nobody's
checked it i did it come on that's my
gold star i had all these extra plans
like i spent an extra day in switzerland
to make sure that i had enough time to
take the test and get the result but not
fly out on the same day to do it the
next day so like it was all for nothing
i didn't need to do any of that so the
travel could not have been smoother and
i was super surprised but now i just
feel like oh okay great so there's just
one more piece of paper for travel
travel is back on the menu great this is
the thing that you can do so uh yeah it
was perfectly smooth so you went
straight back into your old way so when
i when we traveled to romania a few
months ago
i noticed like as we were talking about
on the show right that i had lost some
of my like
traveling confidence because things were
more complicated but for you it feels
like you were just straight back into
old gray mode yeah i think it helped
that i had the two flights so on my
flight out to switzerland i was a bit
like oh my god everything like airports
are so big am i agoraphobic now i don't
know i did have that a little bit on the
way out but by the time i was on the way
back like you know it's a
shock surprise there's not many like
zurich to raleigh direct flights so i
had to take a couple flights to uh to
make it to north carolina but by that
point like
then i just felt totally normal it's
like okay i'm just on a plane for a
while this feels normal uh oh i have to
change at an airport and get on another
plane and it just feels totally normal
so yeah i think by flight two
it's like oh i got my travel mojo right
back and no problems whatsoever so yeah
i'm feeling great about it yeah i was
totally fine on the planes it was the
airports were complicated because like
there were more steps that we had to
to go through maybe that's gonna change
like we're hoping to take a vacation in
in like a month or so
and it will include similar to you like
a bunch of plane trips like it's not
just a simple like you could just get on
one get off and you're there and maybe
that will help kick me in a little bit i
really would like to not
have regressed
in that because i used to be such a
nervous traveler and i really just don't
don't want that i've not i tell you i
have not got my packing situation under
control like we take it a couple of like
little weekend breaks in the last month
or so
and
my packing situation is just it's a
nightmare and i'm not really sure what i
have to do to get that back under
control again i feel like i've forgotten
how to pack
i'm completely with you there i already
have i've been making a bunch of notes
on this trip of all of the things that i
forgot that i do need to bring so so
that part of it yes like that's still
more uncertain just because i'm out of
the habit but i feel like you and i have
both gone through the same process with
travel of like starting as very nervous
travelers then doing it a bunch and
feeling like okay now we're confident
haha business travelers and then falling
out of it during covid but i i expect
that you'll get back into it very
quickly as well like when you once you
do another complicated travel situation
you'll go oh okay this is this is fine
and then you can also start making all
the notes for the things that you need
you're like oh right
i need a time machine drive i need a
little external drive because i can't
have footage that i'm shooting in just
one location because one location is
none location but i just totally forgot
like oh yeah you need this this thing
with you so i have a bunch of those
little things we might talk about this
in a couple of months time but i i don't
plan to ever travel the same amount that
i used to oh a couple of months time
interesting okay in a couple of months
time what's in a couple of months time i
have no idea around the turn of the year
yeah
interesting and so i just don't plan to
to do that anymore i you know i will
still i expect travel more than i have
at certain points in my life but not to
the level of like 10 trips a year or
whatever it was that i was doing in like
2018 2019. well i look forward to
hearing much more about that
so this this trip these trips are mostly
like relaxation focused for you right
how has that been am i right in assuming
that that it's been it's been kind of
like get out of the usual flow take a
break in some ways kind of thing i don't
know they've been it's been a real mix i
wouldn't say it's a clear like one thing
or the other
at the start of the year i did say like
i'm going to see my parents and my
family before the end of the year like i
just don't care what happens and so that
was part of this trip it's like okay
it's september
like work if you're really gonna do this
you need to do this at some point so
that's part of what this was about but
part of it was also working and so one
of the things that i did is the reason
that i went to switzerland
is
that was actually a
writer's retreat thing that i was doing
with a couple of friends i know i know
it sounds so fancy did you wear a beret
the whole time yes i wore a beret and i
was smoking a cigarette
i was looking into the mountains bonjour
everyone
yeah
i mean it was in the french-speaking
part of switzerland which was hilarious
good old french people always refusing
to speak english even when you know they
can understand you perfectly well
it's like oh they're always holding up
that stereotype i always think oh that's
not real that's just a thing people
think but no it's totally real but yeah
so it was it was great and it is a thing
that you know like i do work trips on my
own you know graduations where i'm just
doing it like a dedicated period of work
you know i've been lucky enough to be
invited to some of these things
with some people and this is one that a
couple of friends
had been
trying to arrange before the whole
pandemic started and then is one of
these things that we just kept pushing
back several months at a time for a year
and a half
until finally all of our schedules lined
up so that experience is a
really intense
working experience that's hard to
describe because i feel like even on my
own
when i do little gracations to just
write and i'm by myself
those experiences are often
very draining and like very focused
times
but when you
also have a few other people there who
are there to do the same thing
and you're also kind of checking in with
each other on the at the end of the day
of like hey what did everybody get up to
it is
really intensive it's a really focused
amount of work and it was a great
experience to one be able to travel to a
different place
to be able to see some friends who have
been trying to meet up with for a long
time
and then three be in an environment
where i have you know what i think of as
like colleagues and we're all there to
do the same thing which is get a lot of
writing done in a short period of time
and so it basically got an entire script
written in the i don't remember exactly
like
nine days i was there which is pretty
great but it was
very exhausting by the end of it like i
was
completely
tapped out just like no energy left
can't do anything
just got on a plane and and flew to
america so uh yeah that was that was the
first part of the travel which was
very very work intensive like quite
easily one of the most intensive say 10
days of work that i'll do all year
partly because other people are there
and like we're checking in with each
other and we're all here to do the same
thing so it's very focused very intense
i have some questions about this uh
experience okay what are your questions
everybody's working on their own
projects yeah no one's working together
there isn't like a theme like uh over
like we're all gonna write a script
about such and such topic no no no
there's there's no theme okay there's no
structure to it no because also we're
not all the same
kinds of writers like we're writing
different sorts of things so it doesn't
make sense to say like oh we all have to
write a script because not everybody is
writing a script yeah so everybody has
their own stuff that they're working on
and there's there's just like a very
vague at the start of it oh okay
there's things we want to try to
accomplish and so for me it was i wanted
to try to take a script that was
basically
just barely started and bring it to
completion by the end and so i was able
to do that and other people had their
own targets for things that they were
working on right and every day you're
like checking in with each other this is
how much i did today do you set like are
there targets set in the day like i want
to get this far through and then you
talk about if you did that or what does
that look like yeah some some people did
that some people had specific goals of
like oh i need to hit a particular word
count or oh i need to finish this
particular section i didn't do that
because i never find yeah i just don't
find the the scale of a day makes a lot
of sense for me the scale of like the
entire time i'm here makes much more
sense to me but so
yeah just basically the very loose
structure is everybody's working on
their own during the day you know maybe
we we get together for
fancy berets cigarette smoking breaks as
as we think about life in the mountains
right yes exactly
we
oh chase okay
and so then then the only rough
structure is
we have dinner together and talk about
what we were up to then that's that's
really the only set point yeah it's it's
just a useful environment because
you know in in many ways
the kind of job that i have it's it's a
very you're on your own kind of job you
know you're just
reading about stuff and then you're
trying to write things and summarize it
and it's like a very very solo job
and it is useful sometimes to be able to
bounce ideas off of colleagues
and it's particularly useful to be able
to bounce ideas off of
people who do similar work but maybe in
a slightly different way or a slightly
different field so you can get just a
different take on things so
it's it's a it's a very useful
experience and i always feel very lucky
when i get invited to one of these kinds
of things because it's um i've always
found it really beneficial
do you not like think about trying to
find a way to keep that as an ongoing
thing or do you think it can only work
in these short breaks in person for me
it only works in these short bursts
there's a lot of things that i find
effective
in much smaller doses that as ongoing
things i just don't find effective
probably like partly the novelty of the
trip helps
that yeah so i think novelty is a big
part of it i can convince my brain to be
super serious about it
in a really constrained amount of time
it's like okay we have to be working at
no jokesies
uh you know that that's also why like it
makes it more serious when you travel to
a different spot it's like no no i'm
very serious about this like i've taken
time to go someplace right why else
would i be here if i wasn't actually
getting the work done like if i wasn't
going to get the work done what was the
freaking point in making this trip yes
exactly
and like so i have i've i've tried at
various times these kinds of um and just
to be clear i'm not knocking this i'm
just saying it doesn't work for me the
sort of thing where you try to you know
on a much more regular basis say like oh
check in with people every other day or
every week about what you've been doing
and i i just find that i'm not able to
maintain it over a long period of time
and my brain starts to
i don't know just like not take it
seriously anymore and so it doesn't work
so yeah it does sound like oh shouldn't
you just do that all the time it's like
no it actually works so well precisely
because it doesn't happen all the time
yeah it's it's the same reason that it's
like oh i take the vacations i know not
recently but like you know on occasion i
take them to go do an intense period of
work
and it's always super productive because
my brain takes it really seriously
but
let's say i went somewhere new every
week to try to always just be writing
really intensely i think that wouldn't
last two weeks i think by week three i'd
go oh this is dumb it's quite reductive
right like it's like me just saying why
don't you just work hard every week
what's your problem like i understand
like i understand the
why the question is so is is is
on the face of it makes sense but in
actuality it's pretty silly right it's
like no i i don't like here's the thing
i don't think it's a silly question
because this is
part of
knowing about yourself and so
like it's quite interesting but like one
of the people i was with
he does do the thing where he has
someone to check in with him every day
about what he's working on and like he
finds that very effective yeah and this
is where you have to figure out like
what works for you i just find like that
doesn't work for me i become almost
weirdly resentful of like having to
check in with someone it feels like oh
am i in school is this homework
it's just like it completely doesn't
work you have to figure out what works
for you in your own life i think it's
this is also one of the reasons why it's
very useful um in these kinds of things
to talk to other people about like oh
how do you write how do you write and
you can sometimes pick up ideas and say
oh that's something interesting i never
thought of like i'll give that a try and
see if it works and if it does like it
becomes part of your routine and if it
doesn't it just doesn't it's an
interesting and valuable experience but
it's it's not something
you know it's not something i could do
every month i think
i would either die from exhaustion or it
would just rapidly become completely
ineffective and my brain would just be
like we can't take it seriously
we're not here to work we're on vacation
in switzerland like no brain no
that's not what we're doing at all we
have to
we have to write scripts you know to pay
the bills to be able to do these writing
trips like you can't
you can't just wander off and think that
this is a vacation that's not what this
is at all so that's what would happen i
think if it was more regular yeah okay
that makes sense
so then from switzerland
we went out to north carolina was that
more of a is this been more of a
relaxing time
well
so here's what i would say happened
i don't know if you remember mike
constant talk of the swamp of
uncertainty that i was living in yep i
think in in some ways
it worked out great to be able to do
this writing trip with some friends
and in other ways it was a
terrible decision
because
after having the sharks project
followed by
the tiffany project
and then immediately going into the most
intense you know week 10 days of of work
that i've had in a year and a half
i really was just
you know i was like barely alive when i
got on that plane it was it was brutally
exhausting
oh it also doesn't help that the poem
video that i was working on
one of my main goals with that thing was
i was like oh i absolutely have to get
this done before i go on the writing
trip like i need to be completely done
with that project but guess what it
wasn't done like i didn't finish it in
time so the first few days i was there i
was really like
just
busting my butt trying to finish up the
last few details on that poem video
and get it done
and also i was like oh i need to film a
thing at the end and so some very uh
sharp-eyed viewers did notice that those
mountains are like oh those look like
swiss mountains and guess what viewers
you're exactly correct at the end like
those are mountains in switzerland that
that was funny for me because i watched
the
version without that at the end right
and
uh i
remember we were sitting down one day
and saying tweeting oh did you want to
watch the new gray video oh yeah let's
watch it so it's like i'll watch it
again and then that happened i was like
oh he didn't finish it in time
because i knew where you were i knew
where you were going and i kind of maybe
wasn't aware of the timelines and it was
just very funny to me it's like oh
you're still working on it yeah it was
it was really terrible there's like just
one of these combinations of like too
many things went wrong and also
that project like it would just take
hours and hours to render on my computer
and so like i just ran into these delays
of it it it lasted until the trip to
switzerland that video though did give
us like one of the great out of time
moments so in our episode out of time
you're like i don't know this video
feels like it's gonna be terrible
and it's got like 50 more views than the
video it's about which is fantastic yeah
that is still a little confusing to me
um that is a case where i was definitely
very wrong in my prediction of how that
video would do and so yeah because the
title i think the title will really help
someone dead ruin my life again i think
that tie it was really good like it's
just a good title yeah but don't say
that it makes me so sad yeah i know i
know i hate the title game on youtube
well we both do more texans know that we
both really hate that stuff but it's
it's just a genuinely good title i i
don't really feel like it's a clickbaity
title per se it's just a good title for
that video and it is it's very
representative of the content yeah i
don't think it's clickbait either
because it is representative but it's
still it does make me sad that oh if i
happen to have a worse title i'm fairly
certain my prediction of this video
won't do very very well would be more
accurate and that makes me really sad in
my heart but you know again if you
subscribe to more text you can listen to
me cry about how i don't like how you
have to have clever titles for your
videos um like a big baby get more
text.com
getmoretext.com
but yeah so that like this was part of
the problem is like i had
two nightmare projects in a row one of
which split into two videos the second
video ended up being what like i don't
know a half an hour almost it was like
forever long feature length is that how
i keep describing it
video
yeah it's a feature length video and
then also my only goal in life was i
have to finish this stupid poem video
before i go on this writer's retreat and
i completely failed and so then i was
like just rushing so hard to finish it
on the writer's retreat
and
you know mike this is a thing that just
never happens like when i finish a video
it is exhausting already so i normally
take a couple of days off like i just
have to but i'm in a situation where i'm
like no brain boom we gotta like hit the
ground running full speed tomorrow
because i've already lost a couple days
of this like only happens once in a
while trip that's super valuable so i
just went like straight into writing
another video which i never do
got to the end of the week i had
finished a script
and then like this so this is just to
like give the listeners an understanding
of like i really mean it that when i got
on that plane i was like a dead man
walking i was just
totally tapped out in a way that i
i i just kept thinking about it like i
think i haven't been that tapped out
since i had the worst year of my life
which was my last year as a teacher
um when i you know quit teaching to do
youtube full-time and like that year was
really brutal and i remember the same
thing like that summer
i was just so tapped out from trying to
manage my teaching job and also trying
to do enough videos to push the youtube
channel over the hill to so it could be
like a full-time position i'll never
forget that first summer after i quit my
teaching job and i'm like i'm gonna be a
full-time youtuber but also i've totally
killed myself to get in this position so
i just didn't do any work for a really
long time and i remember i happened to
meet up with vsauce that summer and he
asked me he goes like oh are you still
doing youtube or have you decided to
quit that i was like it was so crushing
because i'm like no i've literally just
decided that i'm doing it full-time
if you're retired i've only just started
yeah i've only just started but i like
i'm worried that i i
like broke something in my brain trying
to get to this position to be fair
though that i guess has ended up that
that interaction has set like a
an ongoing precedent throughout your
career right like yeah yeah does grace
stop making videos so you know like you
have these periods every year or two
does he is he done with that now
yes yeah so like that was definitely
foreshadowing of the shape of things to
come uh 100
but i just i just like i never forget
that and like every every time i see
vsauce i always think if i'm going like
how did you say it like no i just i'm
full time now actually thanks for asking
but yeah so like i've just been i was
thinking about that a bunch this summer
because i think that currently this is
the longest period of time
in which i have just
done nothing work-wise
since i i went full-time so like since
10 years ago i don't think i've had a
break this long
but it's also because for the same
reason like last time
i think i've just i had never been
so tapped out
from
several projects and then a really
intense working period previously and
here's the thing though
it's been great because when i i got to
north carolina i finally got to see my
my parents see my family
see lucy who's uh still sleeping on my
lap right now gently snoozing away
for the first few days i i had this
little feeling of like oh i should i
should get to work soon like i really
want to
i finished this video script i need to
you know now get this video actually
finished so i can have something up for
the month of october but i realized
quite quickly the way i've been thinking
about it is like i needed to give myself
a special dispensation
it's fine you haven't taken
a long amount of time off in a really
long time
you haven't seen your family in a really
just go with it like just
decide right now this is always the key
with things decide right now
you're not going to feel guilty about
not doing work for a while just you know
it's okay you've given yourself a
special dispensation and as always like
eventually the time will come
when you're not completely tapped out
and you're recharged and you can get
back to work but in the meantime it's
like be with your family
pay a lot of attention to the dog like
do some interesting things
and you like you haven't traveled you
haven't been anywhere like just actually
enjoy it so it's been basically a really
glorious month to have after the
completely miserable swamp of
uncertainty and sharks and tiffany and
everything else so
i feel
i feel quite relieved that i made that
decision right at the start and haven't
just felt guilty it's like no you need
to do this every once in a while
and
if there's there's any time it's
legitimate to take a bunch of time off
it's when you're spending time with
family you haven't seen in like a year
and a half so
it's been great i've been very relaxed
as you know mike been just like taking
some walks behind my parents house is a
terrifying swamp
but it has a lovely little boardwalk and
so you can just like walk around and
relax and do nothing
and yeah spend time with my parents
help my mom out with a year and a half's
worth of tech questions that she has
built up as like a list of things to ask
me great that's what i'm going to do and
it's been glorious
this episode of cortex is brought to you
by linkedin jobs today many small
business owners they're busier than ever
time spent searching for an interviewing
candidates can take time away from
managing and growing a business
and that's why linkedin jobs has made it
easier than ever to get to the
candidates worth interviewing faster and
it's free when you're in a business
finding the right person to fill a role
can completely change the way that your
company operates when you find that
right person this is something that i've
been lucky to multiple times in running
relay fm you find the right person for
the role and it can take you to places
as a company that you hadn't thought
were possible before
that's what's so great about finding the
right person and that's why you need
linkedin jobs you can create a free job
post in minutes to reach your network
and beyond to the world's largest
professional network of over 770 million
people that right person is in there you
can focus on candidates with the skills
and experience you need use screening
questions to get your role in front of
only the most qualified people then use
the simple tools on linkedin jobs to
quickly filter and prioritize who you'd
like to interview and hire it's why
small businesses rate linkedin jobs
number one in delivering quality hires
versus leading competitors
linkedin jobs helps you find the
candidates worth interviewing faster did
you know every week nearly 40 million
job seekers visit linkedin post your job
for free at linkedin.com cortex that's
linkedin.com cortex to post your job for
free terms and conditions apply a thanks
to linkedin jobs for the support of this
show and relay fm
so you posted a picture on twitter of
what i can only assume is a vast
selection of magic the gathering cards
and i'm assuming a score thing 30 30 or
if that's not really sure what this
means can you explain
what all of this is
yeah so
one might wonder they go oh
you so you've just been like hanging out
with your parents for a month like what
can you possibly do and the first thing
is my mom always does build up a lot of
questions about the computer between my
visits and so she did have a literal
folder full of sticky notes of tech
questions that we needed to work through
but one of the other things that did
come up
is
my mom
expressed a little bit of interest in
learning how to play
magic the gathering so
she had seen my uh the stream that i did
on my channel and she had heard us
talk about the game on the show a few
episodes ago and she'd made some like
just little comments that made it sound
like oh she might be interested in
trying to learn how to play the game so
i
completely seized on this
and decided oh great i'm going to take
this on as a project i'm going to teach
my mom magic the gathering she seems
interested
i also think she will totally love it i
took a picture at the end because i
thought it was hilarious but before i
arrived in america i thought oh okay i'm
going to teach my mom this game i need
to order a bunch of cards oh but also if
i'm gonna teach her i need to we need
some dice to keep track of things oh and
also we do need to have a scoreboard
because that'll be easier than writing
numbers down and it like gives people
something to focus on so i started
ordering like a bunch of equipment and i
didn't quite realize until i actually
arrived in america how many little
amazon boxes full of magic stuff were
waiting for me on the other side but
anyway it was very fun like opening it
all up and getting out the cards and
it's been this interesting experience
because
the game
is incredibly
complicated and difficult to explain
i've had this interesting experience
over the last several weeks like
teaching my mom who by the way has
gotten
very into it like she is super into the
game now as i've completely expected she
would be
i'm sure it will surprise absolutely no
one to hear that
cgp grey's mom is also a very obsessive
kind of person who can really get
absorbed endlessly in the details of a
bunch of things
and so this is why i was looking at her
and going like oh you'll totally love
this like if i love this you'll love
this but so even though i haven't been
working in the sense of of writing a
script i feel like i've had this
incredible experience which is
trying to
explain
this incredibly complicated game
in a way to get someone else on board
and it's it's i keep thinking of this
phrase like it's been professionally
useful to me
because
when i make a video and i'm trying to
explain some idea whatever it is
one of the main things that happens as
you write a script where you're trying
to explain something
is you can make choices about
simplification like how are you going to
simplify an idea
for the listener when you research a
topic you end up knowing a ton about it
at least i think if you're doing a good
job making a video that's what you
should be doing you should have a deeper
understanding that is conveyed in the
actual video itself or whatever it is
you're explaining if you're teaching you
should understand the thing
a level or two deeper than the level at
which you're teaching it so that always
involves like simplification you have to
decide
what parts of complexity are you going
to skim over you know it's like that's
something that occurs in my my videos
all the time it's like i'm trying to
simplify something down
so that it it's understandable more
easily but the problem with magic the
gathering
is that the fact that it is exactly this
complicated is the whole thing that's
what the game is is like there's all of
these complications and so i can't
actually decide to say
oh we're going to ignore the difference
between this and that because the
difference between this and that is
critical and it matters and it will be
the reason why you win or lose or you go
oh i'm just going to ignore that this
thing exists but you can't because tons
of the cards will explicitly reference
this thing exists and so a person will
go what is that thing that exists
so i don't know it's i've just found it
like very interesting as a kind of
problem or like a practice exercise
in explaining something where you don't
have the option
to
simplify and the thing is really really
complex
and i've never had the experience as an
adult of trying to teach someone else
magic and i do just keep thinking it's
kind of a miracle that anyone learns to
play the game because you kind of need
someone to be like an evangelist and
tell you like okay listen this is going
to take two weeks this is unlike any
other board game you've ever come across
but i promise you it'll be worth it at
the end but it will never seem worth it
until three weeks from now where you've
not only like learned how to play it but
you've also been able to play it on your
own a bunch and start to get a feel for
it so hey trust me we're gonna go on a
three-week journey together and at the
end you'll love this thing comma
hopefully sign me up
[Laughter]
mike you're a very good friend of mine
i'm just gonna say right now there's no
game on earth that is less for you than
magic the gathering oh do not get me
wrong my friend i was being 10 000
sarcastic i i 100 already know this is
not for me i i tried i downloaded the
video game version oh no and i just
opened it and kind of closed it
immediately i just can't just tell i
don't know why you should be like no
this isn't for me
like just in general card games just
like general card games like i i tend to
just forget how to play them all the
time i'm not very good with like uh
board games like the remembering the
rules of board games
and it kind of just says like no i can
see where this is going and
me and this game are not going to get
along very well no i don't think you
wouldn't get along very well i feel like
i endlessly talk about it but i also
think it is a interesting problem space
because one of the things that i
realized like oh my god how do new
players get into this it's so hard and i
feel kind of lucky that oh i first
learned this as a kid when it was a much
simpler game it's like oh they've added
complexity over time so when i jump back
in i go yeah yeah but i know a bunch of
this stuff like i remember the bones of
it from when i was younger but jumping
in now it's like oh my god there's so
much to learn and again why it's so
difficult to try to think about like oh
how do i explain it how do i simplify
things is because oh there's a ton of
rules
and literally every rule has an
exception to it that's part of the point
so you go okay all right this is very
complicated right to start with
but also there are tons of things that
happen
that like the way i've come to think
about it is
they're not
in the game they're just a thing that
happens because this card says it should
happen now
and it's like oh my god like how on
earth do you explain this and the thing
that's been quite interesting to me is i
can't stop my brain
from working out
oh how would i try to change this to
make this friendlier for new players and
oh there's just a bunch of pattern
matching that's taking place and
there are ways that you could try to
explain that so oh instead of having all
of these things that can put players off
like oh
there's orcs and there's goblins and
there's wizards and some people just
don't like that kind of stuff it's like
you could explain all of this just using
shapes you could say oh this card it's a
square and this card is a circle
and that one's a triangle and you have
another card that says
remove all triangles from the board and
like oh suddenly it's so much more
understandable
it's just like you're just matching
patterns you're matching these different
words that are going on but anyway it's
also just made me think a lot about
what makes games
fun
like like why why is it that a game can
be fun
and
a big part of i think what some people
find fun about games and i don't know if
this is true for you
is
it's not so much the game itself that's
fun it's the figuring out how to play
the game part that's fun
like at the beginning of the pandemic
my wife and i we got the board game
pandemic and we played it for a little
while great idea
i said great idea but i mean bad idea
no it was great all right pandemic the
board game no i've never i know i i've
never played it now i think you might
actually like pandemic it might be fun
but so here's the thing it's like oh we
played it but part of the fun for me is
like learning how to play the game and i
go oh okay but at a certain point i feel
like i've kind of
solved it it's like oh i know how to
play this game i've gotten reasonably
good at it
and now
suddenly the game just loses all
interest and i just never want to play
it again which is exactly what happened
with pandemic
and so my pitch for anyone listening is
if you have this experience where you
play games
but then at some point when you feel
like you've figured out how to play the
game
and then you just lose interest you
actually don't really want to play it
anymore once you know how to play it's
like magic is for you
and it's one of the reasons why i really
wanted to pitch this to my mom of like
oh she should totally get into this she
would love it because i've seen her do
this same thing her whole life where she
learns how to play a game
she kind of solves it and gets very good
at it and then totally loses interest in
it but what you're saying is with magic
there's always something to learn yeah
it's completely impossible to master and
so
like i taught my mom how to play
settlers of catan a number of years ago
and you know she used to play on the
ipad and then i think she basically
became like a world-class player and
never lost and got just totally bored
and was like oh okay i've solved katan
there's nothing more here for me and she
put it away and never played it again
but the thing that makes magic different
is that every three months they come out
with new cards and the new cards change
all of the rules and mix everything up
and so like it's never ever done if the
thing that you think is fun about a game
is figuring out the game magic 100
is for you
but the flip side is oh my god is it the
most complicated game in the world to
explain to another person and to get
another person into and to like get
someone on board with
so there's a funny way in which even
when i haven't been working
i can see that the part of my brain that
does the thing which is my career in
some ways which is
explaining things how do you do it how
do you make it better how would you want
to change this language so that it's
more comprehensible to a viewer like
that part of my brain is
on vacation
but it's also had this interesting toy
to like play around with while it's
recharging
and i'm very happy that i have
successfully taught my mom how to play
magic and she is successfully working
her way up the ladder beating the new
players now and she's super happy about
it and it's one of those experiences
where i see her in the morning and she's
all bleary-eyed because she stayed up
until two in the morning like playing
game after game after game trying to you
know beat people on the ladder and it's
like oh fantastic mission accomplished
do you consider it a good thing that you
can't turn that part of your brain off
what do you mean
well does it not ever make you feel like
you can't like just relax because your
your brain's always looking for
something to explain to someone well
i mean yes and um
here's the thing like
i like to play games
i've always played video games and you
know now i'm just like magic is my life
the reason that i like that activity is
because
it's like the only time that i do feel
like my brain actually
is relaxed
so it's a different experience playing
the game not trying to explain anything
and i just mean this for any video game
like it can be really absorbing like i'm
playing factorio or minecraft or
anything
it's the only time it feels like my
brain
can just shut off entirely that's part
of the reason that video games have
always been part of my life and it's
part of the reason why
when i'm done with a video and i need to
recharge it's like i'll just sit down
and play a game for eight hours in a row
and i will do nothing else and it's like
it's completely quiet in my head and wow
how relaxing it is so
i use games
to relax in that way it's like it's very
hard to describe but it's just it's a
way to be
absorbed
to be pleasantly concentrating on
something but also in a way where it's
just clear and straightforward and quiet
but yeah in the rest of my life i do
feel like my brain is always chitter
chattering away about
how to explain something or you know i
feel like oh my brain is very curious
what's this what's that what's that
thing over there oh how does that work
how does this go like that's always
happening but i also don't think i would
have the kind of youtube career that i
currently have if i wasn't that sort of
person so i wouldn't want my brain to be
any different it's always gonna be that
way you've just found a way to turn that
into what makes you money too yeah well
it's it's like you figure out what are
you good at and figuring out how things
work and then simplifying them down is
something that i'm pretty good at and so
obviously i didn't set out to do this on
purpose but it's the sort of thing where
you just see like oh
where are the skills that you're good at
useful
yeah sure sometimes there are totally
downsides to a brain that constantly is
going like wait how does that work how
does this work why do why is that the
case when i'm talking to people i can it
can definitely be a downside sometimes
where i'm like oh where did you hear
that how do you know that that's true
why do you think that oh if that was
true would that mean that this is true
like that that kind of stuff can totally
get me in trouble in conversations with
actual people
where i think sometimes people feel like
i'm interrogating them but i don't
really mean to i'm just trying to follow
through some of the things that are
being said yeah so there are totally
downsides but yeah it's games for me are
the way to turn that off and to actually
relax
but what i mean by this trip being
really pleasant
is i feel like i've had the best of both
worlds that i have actually been able to
relax and recharge for a big period of
time
and also the explainer part of my brain
hasn't been completely inactive
it's had a pleasant difficult puzzle to
work on
during that time which is also a like no
stakes kind of puzzle of how would you
explain explain this incredibly
complicated thing and you're not allowed
to simplify it because the complications
are the whole point
so that's what's been going on and it's
been just a really fantastic month
although
i have just recently finally finally
gotten back into actual work so again
like this period of time is is now over
well it's been great
it is true actually i i told my parents
i was like oh can you please leave the
house while i'm recording because now i
actually need to work today yes like if
work is back mike is here
contacts much
dot com
subtlety is back
i think we've maybe decided this is a
product that gets a once a year release
i feel like that that works pretty well
i know that people love the subtlety i
always want more subtleties and sweaters
because i wear them
a lot i am surprised how much i wear my
own subtleties yes i'm actually looking
at my subtleties and going i need more
of these so mike needs to bring him back
this is one of those things where i
think we had a good idea and it keeps
working and i know people that i know
that own them they love them because
they're really beautiful fantastic very
nice very classy very subtle you know
just a t-shirt or a sweater with a
little embroidered cortex logo on the
chest it's fantastic we have a two-week
pre-order going on right now you have
until november 10th to get your order in
we're bringing back all of the colors
from last year so previously it just
been blue then we brought in black and
red options this year we're bringing
those three back and introducing a brand
new color
green
so there is both a green sweatshirt and
tea as there is blue black and red ones
so there's lots of color choices you
could buy one you could buy them all i
know i'm going to get some more red and
some green that's what i'm going to get
this time for sure i'm wearing my red
sweater today and love it you're wearing
a red one today yeah my red subtlety is
the shirt that i own that gets me the
most comments of any shirt because
people will literally tell me
oh my god
you're wearing a color like i've never
seen you wear a color yeah i've never
seen i didn't know even though you owned
the red one i've never seen you in the
red one i've seen you in the blue ones
and the black ones yeah i like the red
one but i'll tell you everyone who knows
me they're shocked every time i wear the
red but like ooh but i think it's a
really nice red i quite like it but i'm
also gonna add the green to my
repertoire i really like the color green
for this subtlety so
i think at least for me anyway i'm gonna
do the same thing i do every year which
is i'm gonna buy a bunch and then i'm
gonna go six months from now oh i don't
think i actually quite bought enough i
need mike to put them back on sale again
so here we are get your subtleties
people they're great cortex merch.com
this episode of cortex is brought to you
by fitbard the fitness app that provides
a personalized exercise plan a fitness
plan that actually fits you because look
fitness it can be difficult to do on
your own and fit bob believes that
everyone can be better so it doesn't
matter how much you're working out
whether it's a couple of times a week
maybe even a couple of times a day you
get to take advantage of fitbit's
algorithms that use data and analytics
to help you build in your previous
workout to make sure that not only is
your next workout scientifically proven
to be better than the last it's gonna
have been fine-tuned by certified
personal trainers fitbot brings the best
practices of strength training to you
because your workout program is tailored
exactly to suit your own needs it's
going to be perfect for your body shape
and size your experience your
environment and your goals it's going to
be set just right because look it can be
really hard to know how much you should
be doing while exercising or even to
know what to do like i never even really
know what to do and it's what i like
about fitbit is that it shows you all of
the exercises it keeps them really
varied and you get to see the little
videos and the really detailed
explanations to help make sure you're
doing it correctly
fit bod figures out just how much you
need to be doing and what you need to be
working on to make sure that you're
mixing up your muscle groups exercises
sets reps and weight to keep you on top
form and so you don't have to worry
about under or over training if you're
working at home right now fitbit has a
bunch of body weight only workouts these
are great indoors or outdoors if you
have access to a gym or gym equipment
they have tons of great workout options
suited for this too basically whatever
you have whatever you need fitbod is
there for any exercise routine to help
make sure that you're staying on the
path that's right for you to take steps
to become a better version of yourself
fitboard is available on ios and android
you can get started right now just by
going to fitbar dot me cortex this is
where you'll also get 25 percent of your
membership that's fit dot me cortex try
out fit bod for free and get 25 percent
off your fitbod membership a thanks to
fitbot for their support of this show
and relay fm
talking about great maybe i'm tipping my
hand here oh brand new ipad mini oh oh
do you like it mike do you have an
opinion on the ipad mini have you given
up your opinion right now
do i love my ipad mini so this is it's
been out for like a month now so uh the
iphone event apple unveiled an ipad mini
which by and large is very styled around
the kind of newer ipad aesthetic so like
maybe closer to the ipad air has touch
id full screen not no bezels but much
thinner bezels now nice and thin in a
few different color ways supports the
apple pencil which is a thing that i
think we spoke about on the show that we
in the past that we thought would never
happen i think somebody sent me a clip
of that at some point over the last
couple of weeks which is us believing
that the apple pencil would never come
to the ipad at this point just some time
ago and yeah so we have a brand new
design uh you have one right you did get
one well okay so no
i didn't get one my
wife ordered one that was delivered here
to my parents house and so the box was
just sitting there
and i had no intention of buying the
ipad mini do you wanna know why mike why
it's so tiny
so teeny tiny like that screen
it feels like the screen is
barely bigger
than the big phone
well i don't think that's the case i
mean in size like when you look at it
like when they say like oh these are the
sizes it's like oh sure that's not that
much bigger but it is a big difference
but for me it's not even so much the
screen size even on the ipad mini you
have ipad os so
you're able to do more on that screen i
had no intention of getting the mini but
my mom did get a mini and so i saw her
using it and i thought
ooh
that looks interesting
and then
somehow my wife's ipad box got opened
and i installed my icloud settings i've
tripped my iphone
get up
onto my wife's ipad mini you know just
to like just try it out just to see
you you know my actual critical test for
the ipad mini was is it too small to
play magic on the answer is no it's not
too small to play magic on and so i
may have been using my wife's ipad mini
quite intensively for the past couple of
weeks
and i may certainly be ordering one for
myself when i go back because
i'm very surprised but i like it i like
it quite a lot it seems extra ridiculous
when i put it next to my giant ipad pro
yeah but the thing that has been really
interesting to me is realizing it's just
a very nice notebook size
like it's almost exactly the same
pleasant size as our theme system
journal yeah it's like what a great
little size for a little companion ipad
and yeah i've been surprised by how much
i like it and i've been surprised by how
much i find myself reaching for it over
my giant ipad pro it's a real win as a
product i absolutely loathe the volume
button placement but other than that i
have no complaints for that ipad mini at
all like it's such a great little device
yeah with that with the volume button
thing i feel like they gave and took
away at the same time right because it's
weird because it's at the top but i
don't know if you'd notice this but the
up and down changes by device
orientation yeah no i i i have noticed
that but here's the one that kills me
yeah okay here yeah great idea i have no
problem with that
i get why they did it it helps make the
volume button placement less weird but
now it bothers me that my big ipad
doesn't work that way
right it's like guys this is this is a
software thing you should make all the
volume buttons work this way
makes sense that just because you moved
it to the top now it doesn't make sense
because the point is like the the the
buttons are always fixed and doesn't
matter where they are if you change
where the ipad's oriented the buttons
will be in technically different order
so i it should be everywhere i don't
know why this is just a thing
for the ipad mini but it is as of right
now they should do it on the phone too
like if they make the decision that the
button on top is always the up volume
button for the love of god do it with
all of your volume buttons don't do it
with one of your volume buttons
it's a very strange decision but that's
that's kind of just how that sounds
right now
the ipad mini now is it's the only ipad
i'm using okay so you used to have just
the regular size one right you didn't
have the pro no i have both pros okay
but i so i had the big one
that was what i always had started with
that and then with the 11 inch
i kind of started to move away from it
and then once i once i kind of became
big mac boy again
i stopped using the 12.9 inch completely
and was just using the 11 inch ipad pro
pretty much exclusively at home as my
home computer you know it's like i'm at
home i'm doing things no matter what it
is i'm going to use my ipad for it but
now that has transitioned to the ipad
mini because by and large what i'm doing
when i'm at home
is like content consumption stuff
and i feel like this ipad mini is like
the best content consumption ipad that's
ever been made like
screen is just big enough for video and
it's so small that you can hold it
really comfortably in one hand and it's
also whilst very small especially in
like especially when you have the the
keyboard up in landscape you don't
really get a lot of information on the
screen it's big enough that i can like
respond to some email check a couple of
spreadsheet things if i have to
and so i am actually
now i'm going to be selling my big ipad
my 12.9 oh just don't use
that size class for me is done now the
smaller ipad pro
i do like that i have i haven't decided
that may go but i've not i've not made
up my mind on that yet completely
because the magic keyboard is such a
fantastic tool
and you know being able to have an ipad
with that keyboard right there is is
really great i wish that there was some
kind of solution for the ipad mini not
an impossible task but a very difficult
one like what are you going to do a
one-handed dvorak layout on that
keyboard
space a ipad mini keyboard before
so bridge keyboards they used to make an
ipad mini keyboard and very small but it
could get the job done nevertheless like
so i'm not i don't really know exactly
what the ipad pro will be for me in the
future
because the question mark that i keep
having is like they're not going to
update this mini as much as they update
in ipad pro and you know if i if i'm
like oh i'm all mini all the time
nothing's ever going to change me in
four years time i'm gonna be really
upset because you know they just haven't
done anything with it so i don't really
know exactly what the future holds for
me
when it comes to the ipad but right now
because this ipad mini has all of the
specs that i care about the most you
know like it's fast and it's capable i
can do anything i want with it it really
has just become like this is the perfect
ipad for what i'm using an ipad for now
i'm gonna recommend with the keyboard
stuff like i
think on the mini it's way better to
float the keyboard and use the little
floating like iphone style keyboard
instead the swipey guy yeah i've been
doing that i've been doing that more
i've been doing the split keyboard a bit
too but the floating one is the best one
because you could still just use one
thumb while you're holding it
to do all of that so that that works
pretty well i've i have bumped into a
few applications that don't handle that
very well i don't know why i've had some
stuff like since the ipad mini come out
where like there's been some weird like
just ui things that have been going on
which is starting to get cleared up but
one of my favorite was the
carrot weather widget like the widget
shows you like a seven day forecast and
it would show me monday tuesday
wednesday and sunday
because thursday friday and saturday
would get cut off and that was very
funny to me you know like just a couple
of days would just get cut out of the
widget you know because it it is
slightly different in size and all that
kind of stuff and so with these kinds of
things because they just drop them all
of a sudden some developers yeah this is
always the case when when apple has a
new screen size is you have to expect
for the first month there's a lot of
like ui weirdness oh the magic app isn't
full screen there's weird black bars on
the side it's like right because they
had no idea this was coming and yeah
i've definitely noticed a few other
things that are that are a bit weird
the other thing that like this this one
reminded me that i totally forgot
that i used to do is is like that split
keyboard where you can use two thumbs to
type
uh on either side of the screen
i find that a really comfortable
input method and i forgot that i used to
with one of my very old minis sometimes
take it out on a walk
and use that double thumb split keyboard
as a way to like write down ideas really
quickly
and i've been doing that again like as
i've as i've been taking little walks
around here and i just love it as an
input method i find it just very
pleasant
it's faster than on the phone with one
thumb but the device isn't so big that
it like i'm not gonna take my giant ipad
pro out for a walk and use like a split
keyboard on either side like that's dumb
i just i really like the size of it and
i also find with the cover and ah
hallelujah the flat sides like when you
fold that cover back and with the flat
sides
it's so comfortable to hold and i feel
like i have such a solid grip on it
that it is a thing that i can like take
out for a little walk to the local
coffee place and like have out while i'm
walking and thinking and writing down
some ideas like it's it really is just a
fantastic little form size i think they
did such a good job with it and
i'm with you mike like for whatever
reason apple seems to not enjoy updating
their small devices but right now while
it's new and it's still reasonably fast
and can do all the modern things like i
think it's a it's a fantastic little
little ipad maybe if we just convince
all the cortexes to buy them and maybe
they will update it more frequently
because like we just need to become
complete evangelists for the ipad mini
now which i have no problem being
because it is an absolutely superb
little device i have the purple one with
the cherry case
it's such a nice little pairing and
this thing's gonna like one of the
things that i've been struggling with
when thinking about getting back into
travel again is
i'm not going to want to
have just an ipad with me anymore which
is what i was doing with some dreams
before it was just an ipad like i'm now
going to want to have a macbook pro with
me especially
when we talk about the new macbook pros
in a minute
and you know all i'm gonna want is to
have a macbook pro with me
and i was struggling about like would i
wanna bring an ipad like i really love
my ipad for like
everything i do when i'm stationary you
know like when i'm at home i barely use
my phone i use my ipad you know like
that's what i like and if i'm on
vacation if i'm hanging out or in the
room like i would want to use an ipad
for all of those things right like when
i'm not doing work but i'm not on the go
like you know this is kind of the way
that i like to
to consume content and media and stuff
and if i was gonna be bringing
my ipad pro
then that's like a big heavy thing
because i'm going to bring my upper pro
i'm going to bring it in the magic
keyboard because of course and then it's
like now i'm bringing two laptops of
course yes right yeah 100 you're
bringing to your laptop yeah and now
with this little thing
it just can just be thrown in the bag in
like the book pocket not even in the
laptop pocket like my tote bag has like
a book pocket where i put my journal and
this goes in with it like and it just
feels like nothing it doesn't feel like
i'm bringing any additional weight with
me and it's just
it's made even that
kind of equation way easier for me we're
like it's a no-brainer i'll bring this
ip with me it's no problem i could just
put it in my jacket pocket if i want to
you could put it in your jacket pocket
oh i put it in my pajama pocket it fits
it's an interesting question i don't
know if when i get my mini if it's a
thing that i'll bring on trips with me
but i will definitely be tempted i think
i won't because my perfect travel
solution is i have the macbook and i
bring the big ipad pro because when i'm
working i use sidecar to have the two
screens for the computer which is
one of my favorite things apple has ever
done like god damn is that an amazing
feeling yeah i mean you could do it with
the little one if you want right i don't
know how good it's gonna be you know
like i'm actually sitting here right now
i've never even tried i don't even think
i've ever seriously ever used sidecar oh
my god sidecar is the best mic it's my
favorite thing ever that's apple i have
like tried it but i've never like
seriously used it so how do you use it
do you set it up as a separate monitor
or is it like just for certain apps
yeah so it like sidecar allows it to
function as a separate monitor that
that's really all it is it's like you
plugged in an external display to your
computer
and
that that's why like you know on on my
writing retreat it's like i've got my
laptop and i have the second monitor and
that allows me you know without having
to actually bring a second monitor
to have a really great working setup
where it's like i can have notes on one
screen and a script on the other and
it's like
yeah i know i can put them side by side
on the same screen but it is so much
nicer it's so much easier to be able to
spread out across two screens like it it
really is like whatever engineers that
apple worked on sidecar like thank you
it is my favorite thing in years and
years that apple did and like
it allows me when traveling to just
really get so much more out of these
things
the only thing i'm always wondering is
like hey could i connect more than one
ipad to my laptop because i would
totally consider doing it with three so
i can have two screens on either side of
my laptop when i'm working but it would
be amazing if i could do that with the
mini so do sidecar to the big ipad and
do sidecar to the tiny ipad
i wouldn't be surprised if sidecar
doesn't actually work with the ipad mini
i wouldn't be surprised if they hard
coded that in to be like no i got it
running right now oh it does work oh
that's interesting okay i'll have to
play hey look it's like a little touch
bar down here what's going on i've got
safari open and it's showing me all the
tabs like a touch bar yeah the sidecar
lets you have some little ios style
controls along the side of your second
monitor i turn all of those off because
i just want to use it as a second
monitor because i want to be able to use
the keyboard on my laptop to just move
between all of the windows and
everything very quickly i'm not going to
touch the screen all right well when
we're done with the show i'm going to
have to go try sidecar with my mini i
don't think it will be the same but i'll
be curious to give it a shot let me tell
you it works
it's
fine
any app i'm putting on this i have to
significantly scale down in size but i
don't know what do you put on the site
like what are you putting on side car
like what are you putting on the display
so
usually the way it works is i have like
my script writing app on the main
display and then i have
notes or safari on the second display
and so that's how i'm using it to like
divide up the screen
i think perhaps the only thing that
sidecar would be useful for the mini is
to just run carrot weather in it
full screen so you have like a little
display that shows you what the weather
is i think that's about that's about
what the mini size might be good for i
just put slack there and like you know
it's filling up the entire display or
whatever but it's all perfectly readable
because the screen's so crisp yeah i'll
be curious to play with it but it's just
i don't know maybe maybe like i just i
tend to have apps
bigger than i need them maybe on the mac
in general because i have all the screen
space you know but like i'm throwing
things on there now and yeah i have to
resize them or whatever but
it works perfectly well interesting i
might play around with it some more i
think especially when i'm traveling i
might play around with sidecar some more
it's not really something that i've used
very much because you know like i have a
uh like a 30 inch display for my laptop
and so i just use that one and for my
imac i have you know the imac is 21
inches and then i have another display
on the side that the the dell display
that i was using when i was using a mac
mini on this desk i just turned it on
its side so it's a portrait monitor and
i have all of the recording tools just
on that window so like my audio hijack
and skype and all that kind of stuff is
just on that monitor it's just left
alone and never touched
so you know i'm used to using maybe
different displays situations where i
don't know i don't find myself working
just from a laptop very much so i
haven't maybe felt the need to even
think about what sidecar would provide
me yeah i love it but it's also a side
effect of i'm using the other full-size
one which with my current laptop doubles
the screen real estate and i just find
really really useful and yeah that is
cool though d cramps the writing
environment like oh great i've got more
space here for notes and scripts i don't
have to flip back and forth between the
two of them or i don't have to squeeze
it so that either of them is half the
half the single screen size but
so i will because of that i will always
be traveling with whatever the biggest
ipad is that apple makes i mean i'll
just put a little asterisk on that in
case they make like a table size one i'm
not going to travel with that the
biggest one they currently make i'm
gonna have but i could honestly find
myself tempted to bring along the mini
as well precisely for what you're saying
because it feels like
it's nothing to pack like why not have
it it's a it's a great little size
and there's lots of situations where i
could imagine just wanting to especially
when i'm traveling for a light day just
go out with that mini and not take
anything else so i think i will be
tempted to travel with it even though it
is somewhat ridiculous to be traveling
with a laptop and two ipads i don't
think i could bring myself to that
honestly
i'll be tempted i'll let you know next
time i'm wrapping up all my packing i'll
let you know what i've decided to bring
this episode is brought to you by
squarespace the all-in-one platform to
build your online presence and run your
business from websites and online stores
to marketing tools and analytics
squarespace have got you covered they
really have everything that you're going
to need to create a beautiful and modern
website squarespace combines
cutting-edge design and world-class
engineering to make it easier than ever
to establish your home online and make
your ideas a reality you get free
unlimited hosting top of the line
security and dependable resources you
don't have to install patch or upgrade
anything they have award-winning 24 7
customer support they have the ability
for you to easily grab a domain name you
can use seo and email marketing tools
squarespace gives you everything that
you're going to need to help you succeed
you can use squarespace to showcase your
artwork of an incredible portfolio
announce an upcoming event promote your
business turn your big idea into a new
website and give it that home you can be
proud of and even publish your next blog
post you start with a professionally
designed template you use their drag and
drop tools to make it feel like your own
you customize the look and feel the
settings the products you have on sale
and more with just a few clicks and all
squarespace websites are optimized for
mobile so your content is going to look
fantastic on every type of device i have
been using squarespace for various
projects over the last 10 years it's
where i go when i want to put something
online they make it so easy and so
simple to let you focus on the content
to let you focus on the purpose of the
website you don't have to spend a ton of
time trying to work out how to get it
online go to squarespace.com cortex for
a free trial today with no credit card
required when you're ready to launch use
the offer code cortex and you'll save 10
off your first purchase of a website or
domain that's squarespace.com cortex and
then when you sign up use the offer code
cortex to get 10 percent of your first
purchase and show your support for this
show our thanks to squarespace for the
continued support of cortex and relay fm
so we had to move this episode because
of the travel stuff and then we moved it
again
and then we moved it one more time
because apple had another event and i
felt very confident that we would want
to talk about what was announced in that
event and
we would have been recording just before
it and i felt like that i didn't want to
make another episode out of time yeah we
didn't want to do two episodes out of
time it was also partly my fault i don't
know maybe we'll talk about it in more
text but i did a little bit of like a
trip within a trip so i i as always am
constantly causing my problems with the
scheduling so yeah we bump stuff back
but when you told me like ooh there's
going to be
the macbook pro event maybe
and we were scheduled to record the day
before it's like well that just seems
silly let's let's wait and see and
i don't want to tip my hand mike by you
know giving away my opinion right at the
start but it was great to wait for
these macbooks which as far as i can
tell have been delivered
directly from heaven by angels to us to
use on earth not that you want to tip
your opinions of it too soon
they did it man they done did it though
right like so we are recording just
before we get them like maybe by the
time this episode's out i might have my
my i kind of spec mine out in such a way
that it's taking a little bit longer
like i i didn't just go with one of the
default options like i made some choices
so it's kind of coming towards the end
of next week for me uh maybe the week
after that but these computers are just
they're just obscene in the greatest
possible way i'm so excited man i was
very fortunate because i was out
traveling and filming and doing a couple
things on the actual day but i got back
to my hotel room just in time it was
again it was it was perfect like the
angels were guiding me to the exact
perfect moment that i wanted to be at
because when i turned on the apple event
they literally just said like the one
final word about their airpods and then
they're like and now let's talk about
the max great i've arrived perfect
and it was 30 minutes of glory like
rarely have i been so happy at an apple
event
for all of the stuff that they did with
the laptops it like it just kept getting
better and better and like
i have been dying for an upgrade to my
macbook pro
and it's like man they they just they
delivered on every
single mark and
you know i know a lot of professionals
will talk about this sort of thing but
my experience in particular was you know
that day i had been out i had been
filming something i was driving so i had
two dash cams recording and i had
another camera that was running in the
car and i had like another camera that i
was using and you know what i got back
to the hotel room with
handfuls of sd cards that i needed to
unload onto my current laptop and so
like when i'm watching this event and
they said oh and we've put an sd card
reader right in the laptop i'm like oh
my god
thank you so
much like
no port could be more welcomely received
by me than that right now in this moment
when i've got a pile of these freaking
things and it's so annoying to use
dongles and adapters to try to get it
through and they're always so much more
flaky like that's just the most minor of
things that they put an sd card in but
like like i couldn't have been more
primed to be thrilled at that like one
edition in that moment than than i was i
was like oh my god please keep talking
about these computers tell me more and
boy did they have more yeah i think the
whole ports thing is interesting because
what they did with it really
they made a bunch of niches
of people happy and then someone like me
who
very rarely needs an sd card or hdmi
port
but i do need them you know maybe once a
year i'll need it or whatever so it's
like they make the make people who
really need it really happy and then
people like me it's kind of like okay
great i know it's i have it now yeah
like you know like i'm not i'm not like
super excited about it they could have
just given me and honestly i would have
like probably preferred two more usb c
ports or thunderbolt 4 ports than than
those to be for me right like why not
basically everything i own now is either
that or i've replaced cables i've done
that a lot i have usb b to usbc
connectors uh for some of my audio gear
right yep so like just over time i've
been slowly
changing them over anyway but also i
guess like most people
i've invested in docking solutions you
know so like i'm not going to change any
of that like when i'm at my desk i have
a dock and it has all the ports that i
need or whatever which is awesome but
now i'm just pleased that they have done
it for the people that need it i totally
agree with that like and when they were
talking about the hdmi port i'm
literally not even sure what that's for
like i think that's for external
displays or something displays
projectors in offices is a really big
use case you know like you you need to
connect to a projector to do your
presentation having a hdmi port is
massively helpful for that kind of stuff
oh right okay so i guess that's the
replacement for like those old vga um
pin yeah the vga pin connectors oh okay
all right that makes that makes sense
then but yeah i thought like oh somebody
somewhere is really happy about this
hdmi port and i'm really happy about the
sd card slot and
this is what a pro machine should have
is like these these solutions for people
so yeah back when i used to get really
annoyed about usbc i did look into like
a whole bunch of the limitations and i
and i do think the way the spec is for
usbc i don't think we're ever really
going to see more than four usb-c ports
on a laptop just because of the like
power delivery requirements for the for
those versions so i think they are kind
of always limited to four like i agree
with you more usbc ports would be great
but i think i have a better technical
understanding of why nothing on the face
of the earth has more than four usb-c
ports which is hugely frustrating but at
least i can now like accept it for what
it is i will say for me technically i'm
gaining one because my 13 inch macbook
pro only has two usb c ports
and so the new 14 has three and then
magsafe
which i'm pretty excited about coming
back as a as a charging option like
magsafe is a better charging connector
than usbc like it's way nicer and i like
that they didn't create an integrated
brick this time like it's it's just a
cable it's like usbc on one end magsafe
on the other end that's pretty sweet
yeah i'm happy about that like while i
am trying to
very slowly convert everything in my
life to usbc and i want to limit the
number of connectors that exist
magsafe is the only one they could bring
back that
i'm happy to add to the list of things
because again especially while traveling
it is like like even right now i mean my
parents
uh
i'm in my parents walk-in closet with a
bunch of clothes uh to try to dampen the
echo so the recording is is much better
this time
but like
when you're using your laptop on the
road in a bunch of weird spots like
right now i have a usbc wire that is
just it's under tension to reach the
plug on the other side and it is just
begging for me to trip over it and smash
the laptop and mess up the recording
gear so like magsafe is the one where
like that additional feature of just
just breaking upon contact
is really useful and i have totally
on the road like had some real dicey
moments of oh god the laptop's about to
go flying so i'm very happy to have that
back as well and
you know it it really does feel like
a useful additional connector to have
for people who are using the laptops in
unusual situations where the probability
of snagging the the charging cord is way
higher so
yeah i'm very very happy to bring that
back it is funny to call it magsafe like
to have both products called magsafe
because
there is no safe part in the phone
like it there's no safe like if you trip
over a magsafe connector attached to a
phone the phone is going with the
connector it's funny i totally forgot
that apple called the other one magsafe
because yes that doesn't make any sense
at all and
it's funny i'm cur i'm currently going
to put that one as one of their weirdest
connectors i still feel like i don't
really know what they're up to with that
iphone mag safe connector um but
whatever we'll see just like wireless
charging but make it prettier yeah it's
wireless charging but it's connected i
don't know but also like why can't i put
that magsafe connector on the back of my
ipad mini shouldn't i be able to do that
now oh i really wish they would have
done that that would be so sweet at
least i see at least they put usbc on
the ipad mini though so
you know it's not all bad yeah oh let me
just minorly complain about pro stuff as
well let me tell you when you've shot
several hours of hdr video footage on
your new pro phone and you go to
download that onto your computer over a
lightning connector boy are you made
aware of how slow lightning is for
transferring big file sizes
i've never been more annoyed i was like
god damn it guys if you're gonna have a
pro phone that's shooting files that are
like 50 gigs in size you should probably
put a usbc connector on your phone if
you really want people to be using this
for video production but anyway we're
not complaining about the phones we're
talking about laptops from heaven which
are just
fantastic like i think the other thing
that i was really happy about is those
processors that they put in there
are
totally nuts like the numbers that they
were giving for the faster render times
again i could not have been more
receptive to this because like i
mentioned really quickly when i was
working on that poem video because that
was an unusually long video and it also
had an unusually large number of cuts
and it was doing more complicated things
like mixing in real footage with
pre-rendered animation stuff that took
forever to render the final version on
my computer i think it was like
four hours to render the final version
of that thing at full quality
and these are laptops for professionals
i'm very glad to have this macbook pro
but dan like those four hours definitely
meant like some days it was just too
late to be able to upload the video
anyway so it would cost me a day and
then i'd be working the next morning so
it's like holy moly if there's a laptop
that can cut a five-hour project down
into a one-hour project
it's like
tim apple you can't take my money fast
enough to get that laptop i just opened
my wallet and i told him to reach in and
take however much he wanted out and give
me the fastest laptop they made
because yeah it really matters
for rendering big complicated video
projects and
that doesn't matter all the time but
when it's a problem it can be a real
critical problem and really delay a
project so i was just thrilled with that
they were talking about like these
laptops with the m1
pro max chips can render i don't
remember which one was probably the m1
max but can render a video faster than a
mac pro with an afterburner card in it
yeah yeah which is just that's obscene
i think people under appreciate how much
apple is quietly pushing into
the entertainment industry on the
production side
it's little things like this like the
you know the reason that it can render
that so much faster is because they
designed part of the max processor
to specifically handle the pro res
format which is what final cut uses
when you're working on videos
you know it's like this is all the stuff
that i use
and so
this is apple at their best where it's
like if they control the whole stack
they've
made final cut which is the software
using to make videos they've helped
design the video format that the program
works in and then they can also design
the chip that it's running on to have
hardware designed to accelerate just
this part
like that's why they're able to hit
these totally crazy numbers
and i think anyone who works in the
entertainment industry has to take
notice at that kind of stuff because
long render times
are total killers for projects and again
my my videos are short and small like i
know people who make longer videos
you know and they have to
especially if they're traveling and
they're just using a laptop like they
have to dedicate a whole day just to
rendering out like a two-hour video file
i remember that mkbhd would take an imac
pro with him to events yeah because he
used to try and use a laptop and it
would mean he couldn't upload before he
would leave because he's doing
everything in like wild 8k and all that
kind of stuff you know yeah and people
hear something like that and they think
it's crazy but this is also where like
you have to think about it in a
professional setting where the you know
the difference to mkbhd about being the
first or the fifth to upload a video
about a brand new technology product
like the difference to him is worth way
more than like the cost of bringing that
imac pro with him to render the files
it's just interesting like i i look at
what apple's doing and i think
they are really trying to take market
share from adobe
with this key selling feature of like
but look how fast we can render out the
final video project why do you think
they're doing this because it just felt
like they didn't care for a while like
what do you have any kind of feeling on
that like i agree with what you're
saying like they're they're building
into the chips like which is
really super interesting the ability to
handle all this stuff better but like it
feels like it can't be that many people
like it's like an interesting thing to
go to these kinds of levels for it so
here's my estimation again just from
like
being a youtuber i'm on the edges of
some people who work in the the real
entertainment industry you know on like
big projects
and what i my take on this is yeah
you're right this isn't a huge market in
the sense of the laptop market is tiny
compared to the iphone market and then i
think when you're looking at people who
work in professional video production
that is much smaller again than the
laptop market
so it's not a huge number of people but
the budgets for
big proper professional like hollywood
and tv and netflix productions
they're huge
and so what i think apple is trying to
go for here is
the market is not big
but for those people
the cost of the hardware
is a trivial part of the whole cost of
the production you know so like you're
you're making a tv show
and even if we take a look at the mac
pro and it's like okay you say you fully
spec out a mac pro and it's 20 grand
that's like
nothing in the budget for making a tv
show for a streaming service it's like a
trivial cost compared to everything else
so
i think apple is pushing in this way
because
it's just a market
for whom the cost of the product is
almost irrelevant compared to their
other costs
and also
the computers that are rendering the
final products are very frequently the
bottleneck for lots of other things to
happen
they're the bottlenecks for say being
able to
render a file of the production in
process for one of the executive
producers to watch because you can't
have him like watch your raw version
like that's your editing you need to
render something for him to be able to
see if you're working on like a big
complicated thing that's going to take a
long time you know let alone whenever
you have a deadline for a tv series or a
movie it's like boy you better hit it
and guess what you know like i know this
from my own teeny tiny projects after
you render the file you better watch it
through all the way to make sure there
wasn't a last-minute mistake and if you
make a last-minute mistake you have to
re-render the whole thing and so as you
get closer to whatever the deadline is
if you're working on something
complicated and it takes a day and a
half to render
and then there's an error after it's
done and it takes another day and a half
like you can be in trouble
real fast
and there's huge amounts of money on the
line for hitting you know production
deadlines
so that's like i don't know for sure but
that's my feeling about why is apple
pushing in this way
is they've identified a market
that has a problem they can totally
solve because they control the complete
stack
and who is also willing to pay
almost any amount of money to make this
problem uh significantly better so i
would easily predict that
these laptops like it's their first go
at doing this
but i expect when they come out with
their next mac pro with their new chips
the numbers that they're going to be
able to put up for rendering projects on
final cut i think those numbers are
going to be insane
right they're going to be able to say
like we can render a video file in 150
at the time right
and and that's where like those mac pros
are not for normal people
i think everything the way apple talked
about their old mac pros and i bet even
more so for the next one
like
no normal person should buy a mac pro
they are pitching this as a solution for
the entertainment industry i think
that's going to become even even more so
what do you mean if you wanted a really
powerful mac oh man i want the most
power in my macintosh or like you know
like oh i make some youtube videos every
now and again like it's not my it's like
a side thing for me but i want to spend
waste not waste time or you know like or
whatever like you get a get a mac pro
right you're like oh i just like to own
the fastest mac i can own i'll get a mac
pro i just don't think that many of
those uh reasons are going to exist
anymore because the laptops are so
incredibly powerful the next imac
revisions are going to be so incredibly
powerful and that's before you even
start getting to the mac pro so like i
think it's going to become even more
edge of edge case right i see what
you're saying yeah yeah just as a little
example but you know even if it's come
up on this trip it's like oh
the new macbook pros
the display
allows you to actually color grade
properly to hdr footage on the current
macbooks you can kind of do it and
you'll know it'll be mostly okay but
it's not actually going to be the way
that it really looks it's like oh on the
new ones you can properly grade hdr
footage to the right color why would
they do that like that's not a feature
that basically anyone in the world cares
about unless you're in video production
and even there you have to be in pretty
high-end video production to care about
that i do think that there is a certain
type of buyer which includes me which is
like i just like knowing i own a
computer that can do that oh yeah yeah
obviously there's there's a way that
they can talk about it and it's just
like oh it's cool to know that your
computer now has a a trillion to one
contrast ratio like they love being able
to say those numbers but i'm just saying
getting it to the point where it can
color grade hdr footage is a very
different and also very specific thing
to hit that's different from just like
we made the colors even better so i just
feel like the messaging here is really
like
it kind of reminds me of how ages ago
apple really made a push into schools to
be you know in the education world it
just feels to me like they're trying to
do that now that they're trying to push
into the entertainment production world
and i i suspect like apple has a little
bit of a problem if you compare final
cut to adobe software which is i've used
both i know lots of people who are
familiar with both
i would say the general consensus is
that final cut is much more pleasant to
use but it's a program that works best
if you are an individual you can use it
in teams but it is a little bit more
work to do that whereas adobe is clearly
designed as like a team's first product
but i think like maybe what apple's
trying to go for here is they're trying
to catch people
like they did in education where
someone is at the start of their career
in entertainment maybe they're a person
who has a youtube channel and they're a
one-person show or they're just an
influencer who's like using their
computer to put together videos
and as that person grows
banking on oh they use final cuts and
they got familiar with this and they're
using a mac
and then as these like new people get
larger in the entertainment world
they're the ones since they like and use
final cut who can enforce that like okay
my little production company we're going
to standardize on final cut we're not
going to standardize on adobe because
it's what i know i don't know if that's
true but that's kind of my guess is i
feel like maybe they're trying to catch
people at the start
get them familiar with final cut by
having all of these huge advantages like
everyone knows if you're making videos
final cut on a mac is huge and fast and
then you know standardize your small
production house when you become
successful around this product and then
when you're running a production house
and you start dealing with much much
bigger budgets you don't care at all
about how much the new mac pro costs you
just want the fastest computer that can
render it so i don't know i could be
wrong but that's kind of my guess about
what apple's strategy is here and i just
feel like lots of things are pointing in
that direction
and this new amazing macbook pro
feels to me like it has a lot of things
pointing in that direction all right
gary let's finish up on a hashtag ask
cortex question for today i have one uh
for you from eli
and eli wants to know does gray still
listen to girl talks all day
i was just really listening to an old
episode of the show and i'd totally
forgotten about this album uh yeah
actually uh good good timing for this
question because my various i listen to
songs on repeat go in and out of favor
over uh the course of months and years
and girl talk all day had actually been
really out of favor for a long time but
actually
on this most recent writing trip it came
back in a big way
i listened to it just a ton
and
i think it's not a coincidence i think
it happened precisely because
like i just
really 100 needed to get right back into
writing when normally i would just
collapse after a big video like the poem
video
and so uh yeah it actually was the first
thing i queued up like the morning after
that poem video went out it's like i got
up it's like okay
all right dude time to get to work uh
and so i put on my headphones and i
loaded up girl talk all day and yeah i
hadn't listened to it in a really long
time but i will say like god damn i love
that album i think it is total genius
and i listen to it on repeat in the
mountains of switzerland
probably
200 times
i haven't listened to it in a really
long time i don't know if it's something
that like you just put on in the
background or just no it's focused
to me it feels so specific yeah you you
you've got to be like i want to listen
to this album now
right like i don't think it's like you
don't just like like for me like one of
the things that i was talking about
around that time i think was uh tai cho
taiko t ycho and and i can put that on
in both instances i can put his music on
when i'm just hanging out or i can put
it on when i'm trying to focus for work
like it works for both of those for me
because it's more like
it's got you know it's got a good beat
to it that can pump me up but it also is
pretty chill yeah he was a great
recommendation of yours like i've added
a ton of uh stuff of his to my playlist
and he is on he is on the board he's
like lo-fi
chill hop adjacent kind of music yeah
yeah it does it does hit both marks like
you can have it as background music to
just relax and you can also have it as
music while you're working which um is
is a it's a hard line to straddle for me
but he definitely does that but the girl
talk album is very much
not background music i feel like cute
it's a lot more in your face yeah
[Laughter]
that's some way to put it for sure have
you tried out any of the spatial audio
dolby atmos music that apple music has
uh i don't know i don't think i've
listened to any of the spatial audio
music i've just listened to the spatial
audio when watching tv sometimes which
is very odd and i'm still
i'm still not sure about it like i don't
know why this audio needs to sound like
it's coming out of my ipad i would just
prefer it to sound like amazing surround
sound but the music is more that the
music is more surround sound than coming
from the phone or whatever and it's kind
of that's that's how it's made to be
like the music is meant to kind of like
surround you that's you know does more
of that i don't know i mean maybe i have
i g i've i've said before i feel like i
have a real
tin ear for music i'm not a very musical
person and so it may be that i totally
did listen to it and was just completely
not aware i wouldn't be surprised
by that but this is something like i've
heard this at home i said to adina like
oh try this and she just doesn't hear it
and like it's just different people
reacting in different ways like i have
friends who hate it
and i really like it you know like i
think it's just it's it's definitely a
personal preference thing about how you
relate to it mike you send me some
hip tracks also and i'll i'll give him a
listen all right i'll find some hip
tracks for you i'll load them up of my
turntable and tell you what i think yep
you're gonna spin the wheels of steel oh
sure yes that's exactly right that's
what i'm gonna do uh next time stay at
the apps for 2022. oh my god it's the
end of the year almost nearly yeah we've
got two more all right like
we're moving in
we're moving into the busy period i
guess from busy period period so stay at
the apps 2022 so uh if you haven't
listened to a state of the apps episode
before i maybe recommend trying a lot
like the 2021 episode we basically go
through our devices and talk about all
the services and applications that we
enjoy using i think when maybe we'll
touch on some ios 15 stuff like the
focus mode stuff we might talk about
that as part of the discussion uh for
this one so i will ask if anybody has
any like app service system kind of
related like workflowy questions related
to how we get our work done with the
devices and apps that we use uh you can
send in some hashtag cortex questions
for those and we might pick some out to
answer in the episode and just before we
go don't forget to get your subtlety in
subtle sweater it's only available for
two weeks go to cortexmerch.com
puppy i need to put you down
sorry lucy's very heavy