so here we are on a completely non
regularly scheduled
recording time yep no schedule well you
say that
there was i wish i had the audio
of our last recording session where you
said to me
what if we record every second tuesday
now
because as you said at the time you've
never heard me so happy right like it
was kind of like a
a moment where it was like almost
unbelievable
to me to hear you suggest that we set a
time on our calendar that we could
as i think i said at the time put a
repeating rule on
i mean yes you did sound like the
happiest boy in the world
and you were so happy i found it
surprising and
and uh not really quite what i was
expecting because
because if if i know because the thing
if i know when we're recording
i know when the show's coming out and i
can answer questions that i get
and deal with administrative stuff that
i need to deal with without either
a just randomly guessing or b
needing to pin you down for a minute to
ask you
right so like knowing is great but
nevertheless
our schedule was immediately broken the
first time
we didn't even get to one of these
scheduled recordings
well i mean yeah you are correct that i
was trying to do
is solve the problem of let's have
something
like here mike let me describe to you
what the advantage of schedules are
please please i need to know it's so
useful
uh it occurred to me that numerous times
over the past many years it's like oh it
might be useful to have like a default
recording day that's that is the the
thing is really what i was thinking of
is
let's let's have a day that if we don't
say anything we just know is the day
that is the recording day that that's
what i was that's what i was aiming for
and that is the real genuine like
relief for me of knowing roughly when i
can plan
to because there are times many times
where
we'll have a date that we were going to
do and we move it for some reason like
we did this one
and then the day before i'm like
is he remembered because
you're not wrong history to wonder has
proven that there are many times where
we had a day we moved the day because
you've got something happening
and then you forget yeah i think you you
have also developed a pretty good radar
for when is gray very busy
with some self-contained project yeah
and so like when is he extremely likely
to have
completely forgotten that the outside
world exists like i think you've gotten
a good sense for that over the years so
so you're not
you're not wrong honestly the last
couple of weeks have been like a real
good
like you know from the time before uh
you put out the grey was wrong video to
now like
i could i can sense when you're off the
radar a little bit
right and you know at that time it's
like fine like i know if
something's urgent i can flag you down
but otherwise i'm just gonna like batch
up my questions and we'll deal with them
later on right
yeah exactly um and so when that happens
i know that there is a strong likelihood
that if i can tell that you're still in
that mode
i need to like really triple confirm
with you that you know we're recording
yes yes yeah you're not wrong you're not
wrong at all
but yeah so i've just been trying to do
a bunch of much more longer term
planning and just thinking things
through and i was like oh hey
what i would like for cortex is just
some like
you said it exactly correctly i was
trying to think i want a repeating rule
for this
that can just be the default if we don't
say anything else
but then you are correct that we agreed
on that and probably
not but two days later like my whole
life
exploded and he's like well i'm gonna be
shockingly busy until this thing is done
so uh it didn't even occur to me when i
was like we gotta move back that cortex
recording date like this isn't happening
and i think the first thing he said to
me is like oh you've already broken the
schedule that you
you probably didn't get to one we didn't
even get to
one i'm so sorry mike
but look i had notice all i ever want is
notice
you know you just mentioned something
like i want to come back to the
scheduling thing
a little bit because like you are doing
some interesting stuff with scheduling
at the moment in your life which is it's
very fascinating to me you just put up a
video called weekend wednesday like you
have
not only you've completely upended what
a week looks like so yes you are doing
some interesting things
well yeah well you're also breaking the
timeline here mike because i haven't put
it up yet we're recording before it goes
out
no but we've specifically said we're
gonna wait although you've made that
promise
that you've made to me again a million
times where it's
i have a video that's coming now right
definitely coming out tuesday
yeah no 100 it's coming out tuesday mike
i believe that you believe
it right right which is why when i just
had to tell someone when the episode was
coming out
i said most likely wednesday right
because it could be thursday because the
video might come out on tuesday
because that's also like a thing that's
happened many times
and i'm not criticizing right like but
what i'm all i'm trying to prove in this
discussion here is
we're a good team because i know how you
work
right it's very kind of you yes that's
excellent i mean but it's you know yeah
yeah
people work in different ways like
cortex is
a thing that you do but you have a much
more time consuming thing that you do
podcasts are the thing that i do like
there's like it's all different
right like yeah you know this could
easily be the other way around but it's
not like this is just the way that it is
and
i'm more flexible in my schedule than
yours can be because there are like much
more dependencies so like anyway but
there was something you mentioned around
you were saying about like looking at
your schedule and thinking about things
it pointed to something that i've been
acutely aware of right now and then i'm
referring to
as being pandemic busy okay that i think
is a really could become a
real problem what do you mean by
pandemic busy
right so i think a lot of people right
now because their lives have changed so
much
they have like different demands on
their time they're
using their time in different ways that
people are starting to fill this time
with stuff
maybe they have a new project that they
want to work on a side project
or they are taking on more
responsibilities in their life in some
way whether it's with work
or like different family
responsibilities or social
responsibilities
that i'm worried that when life returns
to normal
people are going to be really
overwhelmed because they've taken on
so many things during the pandemic that
their normal lives would not allow them
to do
and i'm worried that like this is a this
is going to become a
problem for people afterwards like i'm
also
really worried about the ergonomics
concern that i have about people
um which is that like people working
from home now we spoke about this before
not considering their ergonomics
think that they're totally fine because
it didn't start hurting immediately
but it doesn't it takes months to like
it's like i feel like
now we're in like the points like six
months right
now we're in the time when people's
bodies are gonna start breaking if they
weren't paying attention
yeah that's like a whole other thing but
this is the smallest thing that's a good
point yeah
for sure there's a lot of really wonky
home office setups where you're like oh
yeah this
this stool and this card table is
perfectly acceptable for me to work on
and then
six months later like why is my back
hurt so much exactly
well like oh i can just like stare down
at my laptop the whole time i don't need
to elevate and get an external keyboard
like that's not something i need it's
like no that's something you definitely
need
okay so so yeah so pandemic busy what i
thought you meant by this is like oh
people are just filling up their time
with
make work you know because they've
they've got nothing to do but so so this
is that's actually a good point so
what's that rule like you know work
expands to fill the time that you have
or something
like it feels like this is a variation
on people
always have a certain number of projects
or obligations in their life
and so like you so you think people are
filling
back up to whatever their personal level
of like this is the optimal number of
projects that i want to work on
they're filling up to whatever that is
without considering the fact that
they're going to need a lot more slack
in the system
when if real life returns
back and and comes in with like oh hey
remember commutes
remember all the office stuff that you
have to deal with
remember social obligations so that's
what you're concerned about it's like
people are loading up
and it's going to be like system shock
later
hmm it's a really interesting point
that's a really interesting point
this goes into my personal theory which
like where i am right now
in my life is believing things will go
back to
normal but it's going to be a long time
right like that's where i am right now
right where it's like i believe there
will be a restored sense of normality
in our future but it's still a way away
like it's still at least a year away
right like that's kind of where i am
right now and you know like we can argue
the specifics but
basically the idea of like we don't
think about lockdowns anymore
right it's like a thing in our lives and
you know like we start thinking about
like oh we should work in offices
now there is a whole other question
which i do want to get into more at some
point in the future where
i believe that office work is just going
to change because of the economics of it
not because of the disease
right not because of the virus right so
like there's a lot of companies now that
are like
holy we're saving millions right
why the hell do we have these offices
right
and so like i don't believe all
corporate real estate will go away but i
think
significant chunks of it will because
there are always jobs that people work
better in person or there are always
situations where like
there are people that can't work
comfortably at home it's not easy for
them
like they don't like it and it's good to
have options but i can imagine a
situation where lots of big companies
have maybe 50 of the office space that
they had before
so like that that's like a thing that i
think there will be changes
but the idea of like the way people live
their lives like i think it will
return to a sense of normality but we're
still away away from it
which is why this thing is concerning to
me of like we've still got a long time
to go
people don't want to be bored people
don't want to be sitting around doing
nothing
and or people see this as a time of like
look at this extra time i have
i have this project that i've always
wanted to do i've now saved
two hours of my day every single day
through not needing to commute
i can finally do that thing and then
they get used to that thing being in
their life
and then they need those two hours back
like it's just like a
and this isn't me saying like don't do
the thing right because
obviously we care like deeply on this
show about people having projects
right yeah but i think it's something
that we need to keep in mind
it started for me because for many
reasons some that we'll go into during
this episode
i am in a very busy time right now
and it's just been a thing where i've
thought huh
i feel busy again why and so like
i've come to the conclusion that the
stuff that i'm working on is short-term
and i would have just felt more busy
than i currently do
but it's about i'm i'm i'm trying to not
fall into the trap of i have a bit of
extra time free it's time to start a new
podcast
uh okay yeah yeah yeah cause i mean at
least from what i know about your
upcoming schedule it does strike me that
like oh yes this is just
a busy time as there are busy times so
you don't think that there's anything in
your personal life right now that you
would identify as like
oh no this is a pandemic busy project no
okay there's like
some social things have changed but i
think that they will just get
replaced but it's just a case of like
looking around at the people
in my life and looking at people like i
see online and stuff and it's like
hmm it's just been like a little a
sexist term that's just been bubbling
around in my brain a little bit
that i think i want to return to at some
point in the future
but i wanted to like float it by you to
see if it like held
i keep hearing people say like oh
because of the pandemic i'm like trying
out this new hobby or whatever which is
awesome
great use of your time but my concern is
that
there will then be a sense of overwhelm
later
hmm yeah i i think i think you might be
right i'm just i'm just sort of
mentally filing through all the like the
cards in my head for the projects and
things like
i don't feel like there's anything for
me that really
sticks out as that but the idea still
feels pretty valid though like oh this
is totally going to be a thing
because so like you were saying in that
i think it was in your q a video that
you'd put just put up slash are going to
put up have will put up have well
uh that you had a bunch of stuff on your
calendar right which obviously got
cleared off
but it's not like you're now not doing
anything
yeah yeah right so you are filling it
with other things
and and then there's just a question of
is this less or more
or could i potentially go through this
time and have come up with a really
great idea
that later on means way more work when i
can go back to doing those projects
again
i mean part of why i originally
suggested like let's have a default
cortex recording day uh even if it gets
moved
and talking about projects is i was
aware
suddenly of oh i need to really
seriously sit down and and plan
and think about the order of a bunch of
things that i was thinking i was going
to work on
like we've been long enough that i've i
recognized oh a bunch of these projects
they're not temporarily on hold and i'll
get to them in a month
it's more like okay assume these
projects simply cannot be done
or cannot be finished and if that's the
case you need to
like rethink in a really vague way
what does the rest of the year videos
look like like which topics are you
going to do or that kind of thing so
that's why i was in like a
scheduling mood and thinking about it it
doesn't strike me as pandemic busy
because
this is always a thing that i do is i
again i don't even this is not like any
target that i try to stick to it's just
the vague concept of
what are the next four to six
most probable main videos that are
coming up it's just
like a useful thing to think about but
you could see i guess if somebody
thought like you
a a little like enough that's someone
what are you enough like that they could
be planning out their next six videos
and then the travel starts again so the
four projects that they were working on
before and now
also in the hopper yes yeah exactly the
the the only thing that makes it
different for me is that because of the
way i structure my whole life
i'm able to then just push back and like
rearrange all of those projects
but yes like most people in most working
situations
projects come with more clear and direct
external dependencies
and obligations and so yes i can totally
see that that you can
very easily work yourself into way too
many obligations
that like just cannot possibly fit into
a normal person's life
once a normal person's life returns so
yeah i think it's a really valid concept
and i i think you're right
to i don't know maybe this feels like
the real danger zone
time for this of people having pandemic
projects and taking on more like
right now and then also you know real
life returning
maybe at some point on the horizon yeah
i think it's interesting because i don't
know about you
but like i feel like this is life now
yeah yeah i do i feel like i haven't
i've adapted
and it doesn't mean that i'm taking my
eye off the ball
what it means is like we have our flow
now
right like we know how we operate in
life
and so i think it's the time it could
for a lot of people where they were like
all right
this is what i'm used to for now uh so
what changes
right like maybe people are spending
like time reassessing
i like your weekend wednesday idea by
the way
i wished it was something that i could
easily implement but i have a lot of
like
scheduled projects on wednesdays right
yeah yeah then i don't need to move
but similarly though i do always try to
keep
thursday or friday in a week pretty open
so i can have a backup weekend day
that happened this very week so i kept
pretty much most of yesterday free
because
you're working today right right which
is a saturday yeah i mean
the the weekend wednesday thing for me
is directly related to
quarantine and the evolution of the
thought starts with
a conversation you and i had at the very
beginning of this whole thing
where you were talking about taking the
weekend really seriously
this was part of the whole like what day
is it what month is it i have no idea
right
like you lose sense of time do i need a
giant sign in my house that says
saturday
right i thought that was it was a really
good point about
take the weekends seriously this is now
a vital thing
and it's also something i think just
generally over the past many
years of of my working in my life i've
never really taken the weekends
seriously you know this is always the
problem of being a self-employed person
is you know you can you can just very
easily end up
always working or half working which is
even worse
so i totally like i was like oh yeah
you're you're 100 right like
keeping psychological distance between
days on and days off
is a thousand times more important now
in the same way that like
exercise is mandatory it doesn't matter
what you think about it like you have to
do this now
but it started this thought process
because i've always like
whoever came up with the seven day week
is the worst number the seven day week
is like incredibly frustrating it's a
prime number
it doesn't divide easily i don't like it
two thumbs down
to the inventor of the seven day week i
found myself like taking the weekend
seriously but getting increasingly
annoyed
by the amount of time is just wrong and
i've tried to come up with various
schemes for
could i have a 12-day week that overlaps
with the seven-day week can you say
this this is the thing that you are not
allowed to keep doing well
i'll just change time i'll live on a
different time zone that you can't
like i can't just keep trying to do
these things
what do you mean i live on a different
time zone and my week lasts
12 and a half days well okay but so
here's
you know the problem is that the
external world exists
right and so you can have these like
these great patterns where you have
some very old calendars do this kind of
thing where it's like oh we have three
cycles there's a three-day cycle
and a nine-day cycle and a 12-day cycle
and like different combinations of the
cycles mean different things and it's
like oh look at this like
i think you could actually design
something that works pretty well
like for actual human time so it's like
but guess what
seven's a prime number so few right like
nothing you can possibly invent
is ever going to line up with the seven
day schedule
on any kind of scale you know it's just
like it just mathematically doesn't work
no matter how much you try
although i've tried many times right to
somehow defeat
prime numbers like i don't know what i
was thinking but yeah so
while i was taking the weekend really
seriously i just kept thinking that
everything about the this traditional
work week doesn't work
but is there something that i can fix
and
for me at least realizing that i find i
rarely really need the two days in a row
off
and that the two days off are sort of
they're ineffective being
back to back and so i thought okay
weekend wednesday
is going to be a weekend day and i'm
going to take that work day and put it
on saturday
so that i have two days of work one day
off
three days of work one day off and just
repeat that cycle
over and over again and i have to say
it's
it has been i've been doing it basically
the whole quarantine
and i love it like i just i find it is
perfect as much as can be done within
the constraints of a seven day week
this little pattern i think is about as
optimal at least for me
as as i can possibly make it and so uh
yeah that's why i made like this little
light gray video where i want to like
propagandize this concept
like obviously this is not going to work
for 99.9
of people on the planet but i think
there are enough people
who if they're able to have some control
over their schedule
might benefit from trying something like
this out
you know because again there's not
there's not an infinite number of
different types of people i think this
could really work
for some self-employed people or for
some students
and yeah i've just absolutely loved this
new schedule and i think
this is going to last for the rest of my
life i suspect
well beyond quarantine at least so what
day did you you removed saturday right
yeah so saturday is a work day right
that's that's what happened
i think the thing that i liked about it
the most which is a very good point of
like
if you work saturday that is like a day
when you can
put in things where you don't want to be
disrupted
yeah because nobody else is working so
they'll leave you alone
yeah yeah and and uh i mean a little bit
of this
comes out from back when i was being a
teacher like you have these days where
you're
you're supposed to put in like a certain
amount of time before the school year
starts up and i would always try to
strategize about like i want to go in on
the days when no one else is there
and you can get 10 000 times more done
when no one else is around
and i also find like even even for me
it's been useful to have a day
where it's just like the possibility of
the outside world
interrupting you is much lower uh like
with work related stuff
if you make saturday work day
and yeah it's just it's been it's been
really really great and i just
i find that that this
the cycle feels just about right i don't
have the feeling uh like i i did when i
was taking the weekend seriously but
still doing five days
in a row of like real work a feeling
like
thursday afternoon to friday felt like
really unoptimal time like i'm still
working but i'm working at a lower
percent efficiency than otherwise and so
i think like
having a weekend wednesday day as a
break day
really feels like it keeps the
efficiency up much higher for all of the
other work days
although again because i haven't
actually put that video up yet and we're
recording ahead of time
this is one of those videos that like
i'm a little worried about like how is
this going to be received like i don't
know if everybody's going to totally
hate this
look at you you can change your work
yeah this is this is totally
like well that's great for cgp grey you
know
[Laughter]
you know obviously there's no big
company in the world that would ever do
it because too many people would hate it
but again i'm thinking of you know some
of some of the teams of people that i
know
you know like in in youtube and
education land where they're like small
teams of people
i could totally see a small team of
people trying it out
and and thinking like oh this actually
works flexible time exists
yeah flexible time exists it's a thing
that lots of companies do
yeah and and even the people that i work
with are
very happy to have some concept of like
when is he around when is he not around
you know
like so even here like you know i don't
enforce a schedule on anybody
but just knowing like what days is great
working
or what days is gray not working even
even within
like with that or even within my own
like personal life just with my family
i'm surprised of how everybody is
thrilled to know like
what days is he on and what days is he
off yeah imagine
if it was possible to like share a bit
of a schedule with people
what are you trying to get make them
happy
collaborate and walk with you i don't
know what do you what are you what are
you trying to get at here i don't
understand the point you're trying to
make
structure great you know people love it
[Laughter]
this episode of cortex is brought to you
by setapp
there's an app for everything these days
some are excellent
some not so much there's too many apps
out there to choose from right
well a great way to discover new and
quality apps
while getting all the tools that you
need to be successful and productive is
by using
setup a subscription for mac apps setup
packs over 190
high quality apps into one and there's
an app for almost
any task so you can stay in your flow
and finish what you started
setup also now allows you to take your
projects to your iphones and ipads with
support
for ios companion apps from your mac
favorites like ulysses
to do and task heat set app has a
dedicated curation team that only
selects the highest quality applications
which means you don't have to spend tons
of time searching for the best tools
and it's really great value too instead
of paying thousands of dollars for tons
of app licenses
you just pay one flat monthly fee new
apps are added regularly
updates are free and all of these
applications are their full
featured pro versions head over to
setapp.com to try setup free for a week
if you like it just pay 9.99 per month
for as long as it's useful to you and it
will be once again go to setapp.com
that's setapp.com
to see how it fits in with your workflow
our thanks to setapp for their support
of this
show and all of relay fm cortexmerge.com
cortex merch.com we have a limited
quantity available now
what i'm referring to in my mind is the
doomed reprint of the theme system
journal
oh it's very serious sounding well this
order was placed in
november oh god what no that can't be
true that can
not be true i had the order in before uh
lunar new year
that was the goal i i put this order in
i believe
at the end of 2019.
did 2019 even happen was 2019 real like
it feels so long ago
okay at that point i really couldn't
remember what year was last year
i really could not remember that right
so i ever put it
i put this order in in either maybe like
december or maybe january of this year
but the idea was to beat luna new year
and for anybody that doesn't remember
coronavirus hit in china during lunar
new year like that was when
it spread because that was people coming
together
and that was that right so it is kind of
like when i look back on it now with
hindsight
it's like not a funny haha but like a
funny thing like i was very aware
more aware of coronavirus than most
people because our notebooks were
delayed
right but i never thought right like
nobody did i never thought
that this would happen you know i have
no concept of it
of something like this it's just like oh
maybe it'll be like swine flu
i guess no anyway so this
reprint is the order that has been uh in
the works for the best part of eight
months
and uh there the other thing is like i
cannot find the energy to actually talk
about all of this but like
it wasn't just this there were also like
multiple issues with this
preprint this was the one where gray you
may remember this
where they i think i told you about i
don't know if i've told this story on
the show where
i was sent box of samples of 50 samples
and only three
arrived oh right yeah and then two days
later the rest arrived because the box
was damaged but it's like
there's just been this is just this
entire rear print has been a comedy of
errors
but they are available now you can go to
contextmarch.com we still have a small
amount
left so if you do want one get one
and i will say just like we are working
on the second edition
this will most likely be the last
reprint
of the current version of the book so
the second version the book the
structure is the same
but there are some features that we're
adding and i'm changing some stuff about
the way it's printed
to make the process more
manageable yeah i'll say but i'll talk
about that later on
yeah but yeah so you can get them now
cortexmerch.com
if you want a journal get a journal
right now
like i remember how hard it was to get
them printed the first time and i'm
basically restarting the process
yeah look like you know we all we all
know like oh look cortex journal is
going through a chip transition
you know so should i get the next one or
should i get the now one get the now one
look at that
like i'm telling you that right now man
you want a journal
you better buy it right now you are
using one and coming towards the end of
it
or if you think you might be interested
you should buy one of these
because i there will be more hopefully
this year
but like who the knows yeah
yeah it's difficult to deal with yeah
yeah we're working on it but
you know it's it is uh
it's hard to make promises it's hard to
have estimates
considering the amount of these that we
have sold and
the amount of times that we've had them
for sale it would seem like
maybe this is like a a little thing that
we work on like
i'm not kidding i spend time every
single day
on this project right every day i'm
doing something on this project
yeah it is this is a very hard business
to run
yeah i mean we we said a year ago like
oh you can totally understand now how
anybody who manufactures a physical
product it takes so much longer than you
than you think and
this is this has been a real lesson in
that of you think oh
why can't they just make another it's
like oh no
no when you when you start talking about
supply chains and
factories and all that sometimes it's
not as easy as just you
wanting to do it yeah but like you know
the basically the work that i'm putting
in now
is from having spent a lot of time
learning over the last
year and a bit right and so i feel like
i'm in so much of a better place now
than i was a year ago
in trying to understand how to make this
stuff work and
i feel like i'm taking what i've learned
and putting it into this second edition
but the plan being of making this a more
sustainable isn't the word but like a a
running
constantly running yeah product which it
hasn't been yeah the way i described it
is you're trying to smooth out the
variance right
like we don't want big shipments
occasionally like we want to be able to
figure out how to
how to make this more of a regular thing
that's that's the thing if somebody goes
to cortexmunch.com on july
29th to buy a journal i just want there
to be
one for them it's a simple thing that's
the plan because then
like once we finally get that done i can
turn my attention to
other projects that i've wanted to work
on for two years
right that are related to the cortex
brand company
but the entire output of the cortex
is just soaked up by the consistent
journal
one day so anyway cortex merch.com
so i have been on a bit of a quest with
real-time collaboration
okay so i've had my mind has been taken
up by note taking
but i noticed that you'd put something
in our document about note taking
as well oh okay you know
listeners i've just been through a big
thing like we're recording
i guess it's a little more than two
weeks after i put up that whole like
cgp gray was wrong video where i i was
partly like reevaluating my entire
process of working
yeah it if i can give it a one sentence
summary
let's just say there was an error in the
research process of a video
and then you made what i think is a very
good video
about your process which people can find
in the
show notes i'll put a link to it they
haven't seen already so it was yeah it's
just it's been like
it's been quite a two weeks is what it's
been it's three weeks now actually
and so as as part of like the internal
post-mortem of that project it's it's
funny i realized at one point like so i
basically um like i took a week off of
all
writing projects i decided okay after
this
what i can't do is i can't just
you know oh that well that was an
interesting terrible experience
like let me just dive right into
whatever the next video was going to be
i thought like okay now i need to i need
to take some time off here
and now that the correction has been
made
and like all of that has been done i
need to like just
sort of think about the actual process
what it's going to look like going
forward or be able to
think without a time constraint on like
what might i want to
change or you know how might things be
different and it was funny at some point
i realized
oh i'm doing the thing that i think
people think i spend
all of my time doing which is thinking
about productivity
right like and trying new apps and
systems yeah and trying new apps and
systems and it's just like it just
struck me like three days into the
project that's a really funny thing
this is the phenomenon this is a long
i'm going a long way around here right
to make a point no no
this is like the phenomenon that people
talk about that causes like
fomo with instagram influencers what do
you mean where
you as a consumer only see
what they show you right so like what an
influencer shows you so
it looks like they're traveling all the
time because they just show you that
they're traveling all the time
yeah well for me and you with with
productivity tools
we always tell the core texans with
every tool that we use
yeah but that doesn't mean all we do is
try new tools right so like every time
we do it we tell you about it so it
feels like we do it a lot
yeah yeah it's a it is a very funny
selection effect
that i mean it's it's easily got to be
99 of the things that i ever try or
think about relating to productivity
are discussed on the show right
but i'm not spending 99 of all time
yeah it's just it's just funny and i
think this is also unlike the influencer
effect which is it's just a pure
selection effect
i also just think like the you know the
topic of work
is always endlessly interesting to me
like i always when i meet new people i
do always love to ask them like you know
oh how do you work and how does it go
because people are just so wildly
different
like one big slider that people end on
different parts of is the like
how much do you need scaffolding to
assist you with your work
versus how much are you like nike and
you can just do it
right and i think that there's often
like a lot of
confusion between those two groups like
not understanding each other
and so i think the people who are more
on the just do it end of the spectrum
then get like doubly frustrated with
this person talks about productivity all
the time
you know and it's just like there's
there's like an additional layer here
on top of the selection effect but it
also just like really made me smile when
the thought
popped into my head i was like oh here i
am i'm reading a bunch of stuff
on uh particularly note-taking was what
was my main focus
but i was like i just i just realized
like i am the the picture right now
of what people think i am i'm like i've
got two ipads in front of me
i'm taking like notes on one of those
ipads i've got a whole bunch of index
cards spread across my kitchen table and
there's like
pens and it's like it was just a funny
moment to become like self-aware like oh
this is the thing you were like gray
prime
yeah exactly it was it's like i'm the
idea in people's heads of what i am it's
just like okay this is silly but yeah i
have to say
like it was a really interesting i'm
sort of coming to the end of that time
now and booting back up the writing
projects i'm not a hundred percent
settled on it so this is still a little
bit of like thoughts and progress on a
thing
but one of the areas that i just sort of
recognized as like what
really needs rethinking
is how do i take
notes right like so when i'm working on
a project
how do i organize the information
related to that project right you know
and this is we've always talked about it
the section of the show
with the best show art of any of them
ever core right is for years i've used
evernote
as the the place that is like
all of my notes and so for all topics
anything that i think is interesting
like i just
save web pages and pdfs and books and
like everything goes into evernote and
like all of it is
tagged with what is vaguely the topic
that it's related to
and i've just like i realized i've never
really thought about that system since i
first
started doing it you know nine years ago
or whatever i've just never
mentally reevaluated it what do you mean
i mean we've spoken about you wanting to
leave
evernote a bunch of times okay so no so
so here here's what i mean by like
not re-evaluating it so people are like
hey have you heard the good news about
microsoft onenote i don't know if you've
ever heard of a thing called devon think
but this exists you know like
that's a totally different sort of
question of are you frustrated with
evernote are there problems with the app
that you don't like that kind of thing
ah so that was always more the
application not being suited to the
process
yeah but what you weren't considering
was the process like
how do i save a piece of information
where is it stored how is it tagged
what are these pieces of information
yeah it's it's
it's actually it's a little tricky to
even articulate but but i guess what i
what i would say
is this is like on all of my projects
i would just have a huge
pile of like here's all the primary
sources related to whatever this
topic is you know so and i would i would
work through those things and like i
would write a script
based on them but um
so okay so here let me back up and talk
about like
the story of of like grey's history with
the concept of
notes right and taking notes right so
i've always thought that like the way
people think about notes
in particularly like a school situation
is that notes are totally worthless has
has always been my experience like
i don't understand why this happens i
have a
i have a particularly weird situation
with this because
i literally never took notes in school
because
as we found out later i was not able to
read the board
for some reason i snuck through the
entire eye testing system and it was
never noticed
until i was well into high school that
my vision was not good enough to
actually
see the board and so i always had the
experience of
yeah you sit in school and you know you
listen to the teacher
and then you know you take the test
based on like what you can remember or
what's in the textbook
what did you think the board was for
then
okay that's an excellent question mike
uh i don't want to get off on like an
entire side tangent of this yeah
but i have in the past year really
become increasingly fascinated with this
concept
of how people cannot notice
the things in life that they don't
notice right or like how brains can be
different
and you're just completely unaware of
something and so
what did i think the board was for is a
fantastic question
and like the best answer i can give
is i guess i thought that this was like
the teacher was working out things for
themselves like you know
when you're doing a math problem you
have to write it down
it's their own reference material yeah
like it was
like the board was for the teacher i
guess you know
um but but i think the like the deeper
truth of it was
because i didn't i couldn't see the
board i just didn't consider it
right like it just wasn't really in my
world
and this also happened to be a perfect
storm of things because
um the way the the new york state
education system works
is that everything is based around a
series of like extremely
automated standardized tests you know
like
everything is multiple choice even
physics tests like they're all multiple
choice
as much as can be humanly automated is
and so as a student you have a
really clear target there are these
standardized tests
there's like books about how to pass
them all of the classes are are oriented
towards that
there's very little human subjectivity
and so the effect of like the
particularities of
individual teachers was greatly lessened
under that system
right which also means that like it
doesn't matter so much
if you're just preparing for the english
regents exam or the math regents exam
like that's just a thing that you can do
and no one cares
none of the teachers cared about your
notebooks because like that was entirely
like hey kid this is your problem
all we care about is how well you're
doing on our like practice
standardized tests so that's also how
like how on earth did i get through this
without being noticed
and also it like i guess there's also an
elements of like random chance in it
because you had to always
be in every class far enough away from
the board
that you could never read it okay so i
have the answer to this question
which is that at least in my high school
you were always allowed to pick your
seats
yeah that first day of class it was
always my goal to sit in the back corner
right one of the two back corners was
like that is my prime target and then as
close as i can get to that is what i was
always aiming for okay
so so there wasn't the random chance of
like oh i'm in the front in some classes
i was never in the front
it's like you sit in the front one day
and it's like
ah like all the formulations start
passing in front of your eyes
what is this incredible source of
information
well well again like i just think
there's a way in which it's just not
obvious to you
if you don't know sure the other thing
for me was like i didn't know you could
see people's
faces right across the street so it like
it never occurred to me that humans can
identify other humans by their face
at greater distances yeah when i got
glasses for the first time
i kind of equated it like going from
standard definition to high definition
right like there were just signs that i
didn't read and i just figured you
couldn't read them
until you've got a little bit closer
right exactly yeah my vision is not as
bad as yours clearly but
but like it's you know i can i can
understand that a little bit but
there is just this i mean it's kind of
hilarious really that like
just like what bored
what are you talking about yeah it just
didn't exist in my world and
i think this is like just one of of
several kinds of examples where
like you have no reason to notice a
deficiency
my like other example of this is
colorblindness you know like
for people who are colorblind once you
have like a set of tests this is a very
easy thing to identify
but people can go a long time without
knowing that they're colorblind because
it's just like
how does this concept enter your mind if
if it's not like
brought out in an a b testing kind of
situation
you can just think like oh other people
are better at distinguishing these two
things but like it just doesn't really
cross your mind right like why why would
it
but yeah so in high school i was like oh
notes serve no purpose and even after i
got my glasses
you know i didn't like start taking
notes then i just thought like oh
you know look at all the stuff the
teacher's writing on the board how
academically interesting
is that but you know like i don't i'm
not gonna start this now
yeah and then when i went into college
as a
general statement like all of my physics
professors provided class notes
because their their whole thing was like
hey what we're doing here is really hard
pay attention and think it through like
don't waste your time
writing notes in class and so
that ended up being like my first formal
exposure to notes was like
don't bother like we're gonna give you
notes you know you're grown up now we
don't have to we don't have to like do
this pretend game
when i became a teacher myself i
attempted to replicate
creating class notes for my students and
then
i was immediately told by the school
like you can't just give
you can't just give notes to your
students in the uk system it's
incredibly important
that all of the students are like little
tiny mimeograph machines like they have
to write down
all of all of the things that you say in
class word for word
and so my experience as a teacher was
like
this whole note system is fraudulent i
have to make
kids write down notes so that the school
doesn't fire me
because the school cares about when the
inspectors come
we have a bunch of notebooks to
demonstrate that learning has occurred
to the inspectors because obviously like
no one can learn anything if you haven't
had like written documentation of of
that having occurred
so this is this like funny way of saying
that like i have an entire lifetime of
academic experience
that told me taking notes is a kind of
nonsensical busy work
and whenever like looking at
productivity
materials like reading books or watching
videos about like how people are
productive
i was always really puzzled at
the parts where people are like oh uh i
read a book
and i take these you know these detailed
notes on like what the book was or like
what are the important ideas
and i i like i just always found that
odd like i don't understand what this is
and i thought it was a kind of
i don't know like a kind of cargo
culting like oh this is a this is a
thing that you learned in school about
how people learn
you know but you're learning when you
read the book and
then you remember the things that are in
the book like the you know these notes
aren't
doing anything except they're like uh
just a repeated behavior
so all of this brings to like oh what
was i doing when i'm making videos
and the answer is like oh i'm reading
tons of stuff and i'm remembering things
and the key skill is like
be able to remember where the
information that you need
is like you can just like okay yeah i
read this thing in this article like let
me go back and and check where that was
or like i'd read through books and i'd
do highlights
and then i would import those highlights
and surrounding information into
evernote and it's like okay great
now i've got a version of this book that
instead of having to
reread 300 pages i've pulled out like
here are the 20 key pages that are
related to whatever it is that i'm
working on
so there's a way in which like i can
re-read this book in minutes
like not reread this book over the
course of days
right so like this is kind of what
evernote
was to me it was a really big pile
of mostly primary sources with
occasionally really brief in quotes
notes at the top of these primary
sources
which would be me just like very briefly
perhaps summarizing like oh what was the
important thing in this one or like
this is the one that talks about that
piece of information
like that's what that's what evernote
was for me does that make sense
yeah i mean i will say i don't think
that when you're saying like the like
notes part like it's not no it's like
that's not taking of
of sources right like that if i was
doing what you were doing that's what i
would do
right okay but so i almost wish we were
recording this episode like
two weeks from now because i think i
could articulate some of this stuff
better well that's what follow-up's for
yeah
but i think one of the key concepts i've
had here
is is like oh partly even writing little
summaries
to yourself is like not whatever note
is for evernote really
should be like a library of primary
sources
only there is a useful
layer of what we can call notes
that can exist on top of this
and like and that's what i've been
exploring this past week
is okay let me try to get out of my head
all of this like academic craft that has
built up in my head about like
what notes are and try to re
like re-approach this topic so this
would be
yeah because i'm trying to follow here
the idea here is instead of
attaching all of the notes to sources
you
have notes about certain projects
certain topics
certain things and if needed to you can
say like
oh i got it from here and then later
then you can go back to evernote and you
can find the source if you need it is
that right
yeah that's partly what i'm talking
about you know because because again
like
one of the things where it's like why do
i think notes were sort of weird like i
very rarely would make what people call
like
margin notes in books because
it it always seemed to me like i don't
know just it just seemed sort of
pointless like i don't i don't
understand what it is and i do think
that there is something
pointless about them kind of hides the
information yeah so this is this is
exactly it like it strikes me as a sort
of busy work of like
if you're writing this note
shouldn't that note be in the project
that you're working on because otherwise
like how are you ever going to access
that again
you have to read the book again exactly
so this is where like
my script my like quote script document
often started with lots of
like what would be margin notes in some
sense like just kind of got thrown into
the script document is like okay well
this is the place where they go because
i actually need to work with them
so like i guess what i'll say is like
one of the one of the places where i
found useful information
to start and that got me kind of like
thinking about it
in the right way is i almost hesitate to
mention it because you know again like
we have
there's like the notion nation nation
represent there's the rome
heads like there's there's all these
different there's all these different
like
groups rovers the roams roam rovers or
enthusiasts yeah something like that
there's a better one in there somewhere
we can come up with yeah somewhere
somewhere it is yeah rome riders like
you let us know what it is
what about romanticists
that's that's terrible okay i rate that
zero out of a thousand that's awesome
all right i mean come on you could have
just gone 10.
i i don't know maybe the romanticist's
really like that kind of terrible pun
you just used it it's not canon
this episode of cortex is brought to you
by expressvpn
expressvpn lets you access the internet
as if you're from a different country
your favorite streaming service will
have different shows and movies
available depending on where you
are and with expressvpn you can unlock
thousands of new shows and movies from
streaming libraries around the globe
there are hundreds of vpns out there to
choose from but expressvpn is my
favorite because it's super fast
you can stream everything in hd quality
with zero buffering
and expressvpn is available on every
device you own from your phone to your
laptop to your tablet
even your tv expressvpn works with so
many streaming services like netflix
amazon prime bbc iplayer youtube and
even more
and you can choose from almost 100
different countries it's so simple to
use
just fire up the expressvpn app just
change which location you want to be
coming from
hit connect and then refresh the page
and the show or movie that you want to
watch will magically appear
i've done this myself i wanted to watch
a show that was on japanese netflix
so i was able to use expressvpn change
my country
refresh the application and i could
watch it in hd
no lag no buffering it was absolutely
fantastic
right now if you go to expressvpn.com
cortex you can get extra three months of
expressvpn for free
that's exp ressvpn.com
cortex our thanks to expressvpn for
their support of this show and all of
relay fm
so there's also a thing which is like
trying to say like what are all these
people up to like this has become this
popular genre and figuring things out
and so anyway like while wandering
around the internet
i found another like really
really niche like sub-community of this
kind of thing
which i'm going to call the zettle
zealots what is that
so i came across this note-taking system
which is called zettelkaston and
i i refuse i refuse
uh yeah z-e-t-t-l-e k-a-s-t-e-n
zettle casten settle constant is this
german yeah
it is german uh and and some of the
some of the zettel zealots will insist
that you should say it in german like
so it should be to settle and it's like
no like
hard like i have this for vedina um it's
like because of her her surname nyantsu
yeah that that ts sound yeah she would
say to me it's it's the
sound in pizza right so it's zeddle
custom
i guess something like that and now
every german just laughed at me but
yeah yeah i know the sound like yeah i
have the same thing with dutch where
like there's sounds that i can hear in
it and like i can identify that sound
but i just i cannot
reproduce it properly so anyway i'm
going to say zettle casted and
and there's like this community of like
zettle zealots but there's
there's some interesting stuff in here
and like i don't want to get into the
whole thing
is this an app i can't it doesn't look
like it's an app oh mike you're going to
make me get into the whole thing no
it's a system right it's a system right
it's a system
and the best way i can i can sort of
explain it is like
like with anything i'm not really
interested
in the system itself it's like oh
there there was a person who invented
the system and
he wrote a million books because of it
and it's like okay great like all that
lore
whatever like i'm just here i'm here as
like a value vampire to just
extract whatever happens to be useful to
me from this system of yours
right and one of the key concepts that
i've come across which just like
it was never clear in my mind was this
distinction between
sources and notes and so this is this is
what i'm getting at with like
with evernote it's like the moment
you're writing anything
in in evernote like that's the wrong
place for it evernote is where primary
sources
exist and your script
is is the place where like the script is
the project
that you know that should be like the
words that you're going to record into a
microphone to turn
into a video but there does additionally
exist a category of useful writing
which we can call notes and
the one of the valuable ideas that i've
extracted
from the zettlecaston system is
it just fits in perfectly with stuff
that i've done before of like okay
you're thinking of notes like when you
were in school and you're supposed to
have like a three-ring binder
that tells you everything you ever
wanted to never know
about the english civil war right or
whatever it's like no forget that
instead what you want are like
index cards think of it in a physical
way you've got a whole bunch of index
cards
and each index card is a note and each
note
should be a single idea
about this topic or it should be a
single summary of a primary source that
exists
elsewhere and these are your notes on
the topic
and coming across this i felt like oh
this is a huge relief
because it felt like two things one it
reminded me
of forever ago coming across getting
things done
where it was really important for
someone to create this distinction of
you have to do lists but there's two
things here there's
projects and there's actions and like a
lot of your problem around to-do lists
is that you're not drawing this
distinction in your mind
and i think like i'd never had this just
pointed out in a clear way of like
primary sources and notes
and that notes exist as like
atomic individual ideas
you're not trying to like recreate a
whole book with your notes
you're trying to have like a stack of
index cards with information about this
topic
that you can look at and like this has
been incredibly helpful
and it was also like oh this is perfect
because i realize like quite naturally
this is a thing that i've sort of done
many times when i'm stuck with a project
which is okay
stop looking at it on your computer you
know write out some of the basic ideas
on
index cards and like put them on a table
in front of you and sort of think about
it for a while and like
you know as we've discussed many times
being able to work with paper is often
quite clarifying
when you're having problems in a digital
system i think i'm struggling to
understand a little bit yes plea
here's the thing please ask questions
because
it's also helpful to me at this point to
clarify because like a lot of this stuff
is still not
perfectly settled in my mind but i feel
like i'm on
the right track with a really
important re-evaluation of how the
system works going
forward that i haven't reevaluated in
like a long time in this way
all right so i have two things i want to
do one is i think i've found a summary
of the method on wikipedia but i'll
leave that for a minute yeah no
right i'll leave that for a minute
because i might not need to get to this
we're gonna tell you right now
don't read anything about it it won't
help you right so then i'm trying to
understand then
what this new system is for you and why
zettle custom is involved at all
because all right let's say you've read
a research paper
and there are things in that research
paper that you want to remember
they're like notes that you want to take
right where do they
go don't worry about the app or whatever
but like do you have a
separate place right now that you'll put
quotes and thoughts
in uh okay so so yeah right now since
i'm i'm still
i'm still in the playing around with it
phase but let's talk about the idea in
the abstract right
so as you're reading through some
primary source when something that's
interesting comes along
one of the ideas is like okay by hand
write a summary of that on a little
index card
and so it's like okay liberty island got
bigger
over time it's like oh okay well that's
interesting like that's an interesting
piece of information so like
liberty island uh is three times larger
than it was 200 years ago is like a note
on this topic
and that can just live on an index card
because this is like the smallest
condensation of us
of a single idea and so it's like okay
that just goes
and as you keep reading through sources
it's like oh there was a supreme court
case
in 1800 about this dispute
okay so then you go and you read that
supreme court case
you find out like some piece of
information and again like you'll write
down a discrete
fact on on this it's like uh no
documentation exists for
why the island got bigger like i don't
mean into
to be like this is like how i studied
history
right which was just like i had a
notebook and what i did was write down
facts figures and tiny pieces of
information when i was in school so i
could pass the test
right and i say that as in such a way as
like i don't want to make fun of you not
being able to see the board
[Laughter]
no no like i mean man like don't don't
get me wrong like this
this is a that's why this is like such a
weird topic for me because it's like
and it's also just been it's why i
mentioned at the beginning like
how can you not notice a thing that
you're missing right
yeah is is it really is like
every time you know you ever watch i'd
ever watch a video and someone's like
here's
here's how i use uh you know rome and
i'm gonna take a bunch of notes on a
thing i was like
what are you even doing like i don't
understand why you feel the need to
write all this stuff over again this is
so
fascinating to me this is fascinating
i can't get my head around how someone
who does what you do
didn't really do this i guess you were
more like
highlighting things right because you
always talk about the highlights and
of the kinder books right yeah so hi
like highlighting in kindle books
and importing books into kindle like
this this is also one of the reasons why
i was always like i cannot possibly
leave evernote
because right because of like the
highlights and the ability to import
books this is
incredible like the scales are falling
from my eyes
right now i get it way more like it
wasn't just
uh it always felt to me and i'm sure now
this is why people would always say like
why you should
do one though what's wrong with you it's
not it wasn't
the system it was the actual like
application the data was there what else
were you gonna do
like you couldn't move because you
weren't
moving notes you were moving massive
pieces of information that had notes in
them
yeah which were more like underlines of
stuff
rather than you seeing a thing and being
like
i'll write that one down yeah and and
and again like
the the thing it's it's it's so again
it's like there's just this way in which
i've never really thought about what i
was doing
but part of the reason why over the
years i've talked about highlights
is because of this of this key thing of
like i need to be
able to highlight the important things
because when i come back to whatever
this is
i need to be able to reread this entire
book in 20 minutes right and that like
and that's what i need to be able to do
and that's what everything that's
like the wrong that's like the wrong
thing what you needed
oh i just got to go to the notes on this
subject i don't need to go back to the
book
the the other thing that i would say is
like
what i was working with
is a memory of primary sources like
whenever i'm working on any project it's
like okay yeah i've got a folder in
evernote
you know which is like oh here's all the
primary sources about whatever this
topic is
but i'm also able to remember very well
like oh i read this thing in that thing
like let me go back and just double
check whatever these numbers are right
but this
is this is one of those four systems
because
you are relying on your memory oh i know
right like
everything you need to because if you're
having to
remember where to go to find the
information
the system's wrong yeah because you what
you need
is just the one place that all the
information is on one topic rather than
here's a folder of 20 research papers
all i have to do is remember which
research paper to go to
right yeah yeah and and it's it's also a
way in which like
it's just very interesting like you see
how you work and i've just
never thought about it and i've been
doing this for years and just kind of
build it up
i cannot believe it's taken us six years
nearly to get to this
like because this is like when you know
obviously a big thing but like i'm sure
you can see how like
it's fundamental right like this is this
part of your system
whether it's the old way or the new ways
is like a fundamental part of the way
that your research is done
and just for some reason we have never
understood
with each other that this was a thing
right like i had always just taken as
read
what you were doing mm-hmm and it never
really thought that you didn't like
it's like for me right i would have a no
let's imagine that i was making a video
about
the history of nintendo i would have a
note that was like
the history of nintendo and in that note
would have subheadings with like here's
something about the nes
here's something about the snes and like
all of the little pieces of information
that i would find out from watching
videos reading articles and i would just
bring them in
that's my system but if i was working on
your system my assumption would be i
would save all of that stuff to a place
and make inline notes in separate places
about those sources so if i was reading
an article
i would make notes on the article or if
i was reading a video maybe like
notes in a comment like in the video
maybe i'd save a link to it in evernote
or whatever
but then when it comes for me to then
write the script i have to be like all
right so now i need to go back
oh i know there was something in the nes
and this one and this one
but in the system that i always have had
all of the nes stuff would be in one
place right like i feel like it
if i if i'm following correctly that's
kind of like
the difference because you were saying
about taking a
quote-unquote index card and putting a
piece of information on it right
what are these index cards in a digital
system well okay so here's
here's also part of the reason why i
like like what are people doing with
these notes i don't understand
is because even when you start talking
about like oh i'm gonna let me i'm gonna
write an outline
you know we're talking about here's an
a4 piece of paper it's gonna be filled
with information about nintendo
you know oh they were founded in what is
it so it's like 1897 or something it's
great they were
playing card company in 1897 you know
whatever
that kind of stuff that always feels to
me like why aren't you just writing a
script
if you're doing this like what is what
is this thing that you're even doing
here
or the reverse of it is what is this
ridiculous outline like
you know you might put a timeline like
have a list of dates on a piece of paper
with just the basic information about
what happened when
all of this extra stuff is superfluous
because
you can just like quickly reread the
book on nintendo
and like revisit the primary source and
like make sure that you have everything
correct like that's very time intensive
i i think it's it's less so when
you realize like again why were some of
the features of evernote
really key important to me and like one
of them is when you're highlighting pdf
documents
evernote has an amazing feature which
even in a pdf will like
pull all of those highlights right to
the front well and also as well i assume
the ocr is very helpful yeah
the ocr is incredibly helpful yeah for
sure because if you are
thinking to yourself oh i need every
piece of information about this part i
know i've read it in some articles you
could just search for it
yeah yeah it's just very interesting and
having made these videos and have
experts look them over like i have
a really great track record of the
experts being like yeah this script is
totally fine
you're right it's like a great system
works you know like there's no there's
no indication of like
you need any change with this yeah but
anyway so like just just thinking about
all of this like
so one of the key things about the
zettel castin which really
resonates with me is i totally just i
hate the concept of like
notes on a single piece of paper it's
also why like the app that i use for
writing my scripts
is ulysses because one of the key
features of ulysses is they're like no
no we don't have a piece of paper that
you're writing a script on
you know they they call them sheets i
think but it's it's the same thing where
it's like
pages can be arbitrarily long they can
break at any point
you know they can have page breaks i
mean and you can have little
sections right and so you can move the
little sections around all the time
and i'm fairly sure that like no one
uses ulysses the way i do
where borderline you know every
paragraph or two is broken up as a
completely different little section
because i'm very often like rearranging
these things so this is why the concept
of like
you want to be able to move the notes
around is really helpful to me
because very quickly in a project it
becomes super clear like
oh i don't care about this part but if
i've like written it on a piece of paper
or it's like a heading on an
outline it's sort of like stuck in place
and you have to deal with it
right whereas you know if i'm working on
who owns the statue of liberty
and what i have is a is like a stack of
oh here's
40 index cards of like your notes on
this topic
there's a way in which like you can sort
them or arrange them in such a way that
it makes more sense like okay these
relate to each other
right this i don't care about at all and
i can like move this around
but when you're saying note right like
this is this is the nomenclature i
really want to make sure i'm getting
correct you mean like
a singular piece of information
yes right because i think a lot of
people including me
think of a note as this page
yeah so this is kind of why like when i
was looking around and reading stuff
like i immediately
sort of gravitated towards settle
casting because this is one of the key
concepts like they talk about
notes as being atomic right so it's like
each note is an atomic piece of
information you shouldn't be able to
reduce it can i read from wikipedia now
please let me read from wikipedia i
think it will help i genuinely okay go
ahead go ahead
a zettel casten consists of many
individual notes with ideas and other
short pieces of information
that are taken down as they occur or are
required
the notes are numbered hierarchically so
that new notes may be inserted at the
appropriate place and contain
metadata to allow the note taker to
associate the notes of each other
for example notes may contain tags that
describe key aspects of the note
and they may reference other notes the
numbering metadata format structure of
the notes is subject to variation
depending on the specific method
employed i think that helps
because it's the idea at least i think
i'm following is that the reason this
system seemed to
meet with you is that you've got like
little pieces of information
and they're put into a system but they
are
free to be moved around yes
but they are in like a hierarchy or they
are associated with each other but
not in such a way of like here is an
outline
yeah right okay yeah like one one of the
key things
you know and this again is where like my
feelings about notes and outlines so i
was like this seems like nonsense
before you write a paper create an
outline of the paper like what are you
going to write in each of these sections
there's like that is a bunch of nonsense
that's saying before you write the paper
you need to know what the paper is about
it's like well uh how am i supposed to
do that before i write it you know it's
like
the outline's the hard part apple like
it's this is not the easy part to get
you started like it's
you know i always found that stuff just
really frustrating and again is is why
with so many of like the way this stuff
is taught in school it just seemed to me
like what what is this charade everyone
is playing like i don't understand oh
i can write an outline before i know all
the things about the topic exactly how
am i supposed to do that
this is also why like this system of
like little notes that are just
individual pieces of information means
it doesn't matter what order you come
across these pieces of information
right you know like writing and research
are non-linear processes
and by having individual atomic notes
they can be created and found in any
order it doesn't matter
one of the other things that i don't
know if this is going to be helpful but
since i'm still in this intermediate
stage but i suspect it's going to be
helpful
is i have a strong feeling that
this will help also more clearly define
when am i writing versus when am i
researching right now in the video
creation process
and for always like those two phases
have been very difficult
to even distinguish from each other
quite often
and so i suspect like i'll be able to
draw a greater distinction between those
two and that might be
useful like even in my own time tracking
system
in theory i've always had two timers one
which is called like
writing and one which is called research
but i'm very aware that i treat those
two as totally
indistinguishable from each other like
very often i'm starting the research
timer and
it's like yo i've basically spent all
this time writing or
or vice versa and it's like who cares
it's this is all the same sort of
non-linear deeply interconnected process
it's not like when you write you no
longer refer to the material
yeah so yeah and again like on my
computer screen like this is also why
like whenever i'm writing
i would almost always have evernote open
on the side and it's like oh yeah
here's that report that dude wrote about
tumbleweeds 100 years ago like i want to
have that on screen while i'm
writing the section about tumbleweeds
you know that kind of thing but it also
does make it like a bit more burdensome
that i'm always like 100
looking at the primary sources right
when really what you need is
this group of atomic notes
yeah and then you can pick out the ones
that are most necessary for the current
part of the script that you're writing
yeah it's it's like a layer of
information that exists
between the script and the primary
sources
whereas i'm totally aware that i keep
describing
i mean i'm sorry listeners i'm sure this
must be infuriating as i explained to
you like what you learned in grade
school is a useful skill right
it's like yes it is this is very surreal
um to be talking about like because it's
but it's i guess it's kind of
fascinating because it's
like how would you
rediscover this type of note-taking
today
so okay so this new gray system
does it only include text
uh what do you mean well like if you had
an image
oh yeah so again since i'm just playing
around and it's still very fluid
i've been largely working on actual
paper because i think that's always the
best way to think about something
yeah but i have found one of these apps
to do this kind of thing and it's an app
called obsidian
it's funny it's actually someone's uh
it's a very small team and it's their
quarantine project like it's it's a
thing that they've been working on
so it's it's still pretty early
what was that sound this looks
complicated
okay so the reason this caught my
attention and is also
uh it supports latex
okay right okay okay like let me let me
get there mike
you've been found out so this is like a
note app
and i would say this is very much in the
like notion rome
family you know this is this is another
version of like
different people are trying to approach
this sort of concept
of these interconnected webs of
information this looks so complicated
yeah but here's here's the thing a thing
finally clicked for me which was
you know last time we were talking about
how like oh i was working in notion and
i was just trying to type and
slash or and then like when i hit slash
a whole world of opportunities opened up
to me
it's like oh my god i don't i don't need
to insert a a kanban board in the middle
of this sentence but thanks guys that's
right
i think for all also reasons which may
be much more clear now i'd also
largely just totally dismissed the very
notion of apps like notion
and rome i was like this is just
nonsense this is just academic busy work
for people who don't really need it
so it just just so happens like working
with obsidian and just playing around
with it and seeing like okay what's the
deal
you know of all of these various notes
like the zettle heads seem to really
like
this this one in particular so i was
like oh let me play around with it and
the thing
finally clicked in my head which is i
realized
oh okay what all of these note
systems are doing is very similar to the
thing
that i used to use in college which was
org mode on emacs and it's it's the same
concept of like when you're typing
at any point you can link to something
else or insert
different kinds of information and
something about like the graphical user
interface of a thing like
notion made makes it to me feel like
really cumbersome
and absurd but when i think about it as
yeah but you can do this whole thing
just with in an extremely large number
of text files on your computer
there's a way in which like oh it feels
much more simple to me
and i realized like yes when i used to
use org mode on emacs like that's what
this thing was you can like
link to any other text file or you can
quickly include some to do's
you can include your latex formatting if
you want to you can insert a calendar
but it's all done via text files and
that's the thing that obsidian is doing
it's
similar to rome it's similar to notion
the key difference
is that they're just doing it entirely
through markdown
files on your local drive
and it's like oh okay cool i get it i've
been
using markdown to write my scripts for
forever
so this is like no burden whatsoever to
then also do a bunch of notes and mark
down and it means that like
the transition between those two is
ridiculously simple if i want
information to go one way or the other
but so this is like a digital version
of doing the index cards and this is
where like oh yeah if you have an image
that you want to use like you can
include it
in just the way markdown formats
including images but ultimately it's all
just
here's 300 you know dot md files on your
on your hard drive they're just text
files and if you type double brackets
you can link from one to another which
is like the exact same thing that rome
does like if you're typing in rome
you can open up two double brackets and
you can link to any other one of the
notes anywhere in your in your system
so does that answer your question of
what happens if you have a picture
uh kind of i'm really lost looking at
this
obsidian app i would not recommend
obsidian
for you mike no because i don't really
understand
like so you're creating where are you
making notes
well again for me i'm still doing this
almost entirely with paper as i'm
figuring out what's useful okay
right i have played around with obsidian
um but again like just like we talk
about when people are figuring out their
to-do systems like you don't want to
prematurely optimize
for the digital version because you're
going to get too distracted by the
features or lack of features
of whatever digital tool it's the same
thing here like i just wanted to play
around with obsidian to see like
let me understand the concept of what
this is in a digital form
which is you can have virtual index
cards with
virtual strings connecting related ones
together it's like okay
cool i understand that and that also
helped me understand
this is very much like you know i mean
the reason i think you're feeling
overwhelmed looking at it is it's
very linuxy which is what made me think
like oh yeah this is just like
org mode from a thousand years ago you
know so you can have this digital
version but
it's just like the basic idea is for any
project
you can have notes that are just
individual pieces of information
those pieces of information because
they're on index cards
are not constrained by your
preconception
of either like what is the hierarchy or
what is the order of these notes
that can that can come out of it later
when you realize
oh these three pieces of information are
related or like these two pieces of
information i thought they were
interesting and important at the start
but it turns out that they're actually
irrelevant so i can put them at the back
of the list
it's really just about the reordering
layer and again i think
why this feels like it's a useful step
for me
is because it's it feels like this
pre-script
layer where it's much easier to
think about some of the information
related to a topic
without one reviewing the primary
sources
even in their much compressed form or
two writing the script where
there's also this additional layer of
what is the
style in which i'm saying this
information
right because the script is not just a
recitation of facts right no one would
watch the videos if i was just like here
let me tell you all the facts about the
situation
that has a whole other like what is the
style
how is this being told like what are the
visuals going to be like that's an
additional thing that i have to think
about when doing that so the notes layer
feels like information
organization without the burden
of style and without
the weight of the primary source
right that's that's the way i think this
will
work going forward i feel like
rome is a good option for you from what
i know about it
okay why do you say that because it is
all about
like singular pieces of information that
can very easily link together
and from what i know of
rome it is available
on the web on all devices and
my understanding is they are making apps
for all platforms
my concern would be with an app like
obsidian is like mac only
which i don't know if if that's the
right
method oh yeah 100 100 like
no ios app for obsidian is the hugest
downside yeah you know 100 but again
this is why like i'm not really invested
in
what is the digital tool at this stage
yeah i want to come back to that though
like i really do
but yeah yeah but like the thing is i
wanted to just play around with it
because there is a way in which it can
be briefly clarifying about like what do
people mean when they're talking about
linking notes okay
i think that you had to start looking at
some of these things like notion rome
obsidian
for you to be able to clarify the the
basic
system yeah right like i can see that of
like all right you're like all right
okay so i'm not wild here it is a a
valid like way that people collect
information
right yeah and now you can go back to
doing what you what you're doing now
of like making sure that this basic
structure
makes sense to you this has been a trip
wow well you know you think you know
someone
[Laughter]
well i mean again this is where i really
i really mean this thing of
of like my other drumbeat from being
just a person who makes things on the
internet is
the deep deep realization that human
communication
is much harder than people think it is
yeah
and one of the reasons is that human
brains are much more different than
people think they are
but they're also different
in extremely subtle and hard to notice
ways
and this can be one of these sorts of
things where it's just like
something that seems obvious to everyone
can be non-obvious for
someone else or just because the way
like one person's brain
works like a thing that works for
everyone doesn't work for them
well like we have been talking about
notes apps for so many years but
never had we realized that we were doing
this process in such vastly different
ways
yeah yeah it casts back on the like
every time you're talking about evernote
or note-taking apps like you realize
like oh there's something else
here right that makes this conversation
make a lot more sense
which is gray thinks notes are like a
potemkin village of knowledge that
schools require students create for
inspectors
and have no intrinsic value whatsoever
and grown-ups who make notes
are just repeating the behaviors from
their childhood without understanding
why they're doing it
right just because you couldn't see the
board
i still like i do still wonder like how
on earth i made it so long without being
able to see the board
oh realize it like that's the funny part
to me right like it never came up
it just never came up i do wonder
sometimes because i think
perhaps if i'm trying to recreate like
how did this situation even begin in the
first place
i do know like one of the most important
gifts that my parents ever
gave to me was when i was in middle
school they gave me
this like course on how to memorize
stuff and i know we've talked about this
sometimes
and like i remember in middle school
just really devouring
this set of tricks of how to remember
things
and i've always just been aware of how
that
one thing got me through high school
and college is like here's how to
memorize things
and so i also just wonder is like is
that a contributing factor
to how i was able to get by with no one
noticing
i couldn't read the board is because i
was like oh yeah no i've got this hack
for the school system
that just lets me pass these
standardized tests
[Laughter]
this episode of cortex is brought to you
by squarespace make your next move with
squarespace they will let you easily
create a website for your next idea with
a unique domain name
award-winning templates and more no
matter what type of website you want to
build to squarespace
they have the tools for it they are an
all-in-one platform
that will let you build a blog or a
portfolio or an online store a site for
an event aside for your business it
doesn't matter what type of website you
want to make
they have the tools there's nothing to
install or patch or upgrade
they have all of that stuff covered and
they back it up with award-winning 24 7
customer support
so if you need any help squarespace have
a dedicated team of knowledgeable people
on hand to help you get your stuff
done everything needs a website these
days and squarespace is the best place
to start you don't have to learn
how to code you don't have to learn how
to build it from scratch
you can take advantage of their powerful
and beautiful tools
to help you build that website they can
also let you easily grab
a unique domain name so you can give
that website the domain that it deserves
and all of their templates are so
beautiful they're award-winning
to help you show off your great ideas i
have been using squarespace for i think
over 10 years now and i have so many
projects that i've started on
squarespace and i'm going to continue to
do it because it's so
cool so easy and i love the way it works
you can sign up for a trial today with
no credit card required by going to
squarespace.com
cortex then when you want to launch your
site to the world their plans start at
just 12
a month but you can get 10 percent of
your first purchase of a website or
domain and show your support for this
show
by using the offer code cortex at
checkout once again that's
squarespace.com
cortex and the code cortex for 10 of
your first purchase
and thanks to squarespace for the
continued support of cortex and relay fm
squarespace make your next move make
your next website
so do you remember last time we were
talking about real-time collaboration
applications you were looking for
alternatives to
google docs that's what you were doing
yeah because we were upset about no dark
mode and then i said to you all right
let's try out word look out for an
invitation from me
oh yeah and well i haven't opened my
email since then but i assume that that
invitation never came it never got sent
okay because word didn't pass
the initial testing for me okay
basically i
spent a couple of days trying out lots
of different applications you know like
i tried
word i tried pages i tried
like notion for something like this i
tried apple notes
effectively the problem is none of them
are as instant as google docs
and you know like i was just doing some
simple testing with like i would have
word open on my ipad and word open
on my mac in the mac app or
in the web browser and the issue would
be
that it would update the information but
not immediately
it would kind of like you could
basically watch the system do it like
you would start typing a bunch of stuff
you would stop you would see like saving
and then a couple of seconds later it
would appear in the other place
right and like that is not what i want
and then
so i was doing these tests in between
the time of like
us recording and releasing the episode
and honestly by the time
we released the episode i realized that
both word pages and everything else none
of them were as good as google docs
then i started hearing from other core
texans who were like please please don't
use word
i have lost so much work through their
collaboration
system because it's conflict right like
this
we were talking about it's like is
conflict also like you know
there were people that were saying to me
like oh word has a dark mode as well
but it doesn't have a dark mode like the
ui
goes dark but the page is still white
and then there were people that would
tell me all you have to do is change the
page
to a black background and the text to
white no that's not a dark mode
that's not a dark mode right like that's
you making changes that you'll
eventually like
when you're on a system that has light
mode and then it won't make any sense
because the page is black
yeah i hate those pseudo-dark modes so
much
i was really pumped because apple uh
recently released a dark mode
for numbers their spreadsheet program
that i use so much i was like oh
finally like dark mode for spreadsheets
now the spreadsheets are just as white
as they ever were yeah just so the ui
chrome is dark which just
that's not you know it's like it's not
helpful like email apps are fine you
know like you
it just inverts the text color but it's
not like everybody's getting emails that
are just white text
right yeah because that's no good so
basically there's a long version of this
but i don't think it's worth
necessarily going into at this point the
short version is
i've come to conclude that real-time
collaboration for me is more
important than the native os features
that i want right
because the most important thing that
goes into these documents is the text
and the text has to be correct for
everyone and if it isn't
then what was the point in even starting
the document in the first place
like if real-time collaboration was not
as important like if all i wanted was
just to have like the most native
features
i'd probably just use apple notes for
everything right like that's the
decision i kind of come to it's like
that's an application that's always
going to be up to date with a system it
has good hooks in the system and i love
it i use it for so much stuff
but the problem is like you have to wait
for people's stuff to get synced in
and then the other issue i was finding
is that all of the new
pieces of software that people are
creating like in the vein of a google
docs like a kind of a web-based solution
they want to be everything they want to
be docs and sheets and chat
and tasks and everything and everything
and everything and everything
right and that's also not what i want
like i want a focused product
so i think i'm basically back in the
place that i end up being once every
year or two
[Laughter]
google docs is the best at what google
docs does
yeah and i just have to hope that google
will update it to be what i want it to
be
i'm sorry that your your journey into
real-time collaboration apps was
was less of a less of a march and more
of just a
circle right back to where you started
in like two days
it really it really didn't at least it
was a short circle then it wasn't
that's true that's true i could i didn't
have to do a lot of work to come to this
decision
but i just i've come to really rely and
value
what google docs does
and it's the best of what it does
fundamentally
so i mentioned that now was a busy time
for me right like
a lot going on right now and the big
project
that i have uh on my horizon is the
podcast-a-thon podcast-a-thon 2. oh
podcast-a-thon 2. yep electric boogaloo
indeed
listeners may remember that last year uh
we raised
a ton of money it was an incredible
thing for the saint george children's
cancer research hospital
and i'm going to be talking a little bit
more about this on our next episode
but we are fundraising again starting
now and throughout september if you go
to century.org
relay you can give money there it would
be incredible
uh for you to support the cause we had
such an incredible showing last year we
raised over three hundred thousand
dollars
um which was just absolutely
unbelievable blew us all away
and we want to do it again we want to
raise that money again uh because
you know these it's difficult right
everything's difficult for everyone
right now
but that doesn't mean that this is the
thing that we also can't continue to
think about and we should
like saint jude is such an incredible
place like
they do such incredible work the
treatments that have been invented at
saint jude
they've helped push the child cancer
survival rate from 20
to more than 80 percent in his 50 years
of being around
and so supporting this charity like
their mission is to make sure that no
child
dies from cancer and i think they can do
that right like
they've they've done such incredible
things over 50 years
we want to continue to support their
work so if you go to studio.org
relay you can donate whatever you can
will go
a long way to helping this
wonderful institution and the children
that they
take care of and this isn't a charity
that is
just an american charity they they help
people from all over the world and the
research
from saint jude has helped with medicine
worldwide so it is a really really
incredible place it does incredible
things
so say i want to talk more in detail
about situated on our next episode
because that is
will be in september and it's that is
when childhood cancer awareness month is
but also in september is podcast-a-thon
it's going to be on september 18th
from 2 to 8 p.m eastern twitch.tv relay
fm again i will talk about that more i
will remind everybody in our next
episode about that
but the big thing the big thing that's
taking up my time right now
is that this is an all-remote
podcast-a-thon
you're not all getting together in uh
tennessee again no not happening it's
like last year we did everything
in memphis tennessee that at the saint
ju campus they have these incredible
production facilities there
and i mean i can't be there so
currently at the moment uh big project
is getting mega studio
set for this event oh right you're going
to need
filming as well right like this whole
video you want to look good on camera
so i have my one person production crew
of adina right now
and we are making it happen we're
setting up sets we're getting some
lights we're getting tripods
and yeah there's there's a lot going on
and it's the be
it's a big project for everyone right
now
because as well as coming up with the
content that we want to put into the
event it's like
just the basics you know when we started
the planning for podcast-a-thon 2
it was like all right how can we make
this bigger and better and focus on the
content
so we started doing that and now we have
the sub project of
okay now we need to rework all the
logistics as well so
right right so it's a bigger project i
mean i'm really pleased this is the
second one we've done because if it was
the first one it would have been
infinitely harder because now we've been
able to learn from last year
and you know like i genuinely think that
the remoteness of it
is not going to affect it the only
difference is me and stephen are not in
the same place
because yeah every guest we had last
year well
but many of the guests we had last year
were remote guests
it's really lucky that you were able to
do it with stephen in person the first
time
that makes a huge difference for trying
to do it all remote the second time for
sure
yeah so we've learnt from it and we have
an incredible team
at st jude and ulsak to help us put it
on
like they've given us access to lots of
incredible resources
so i'm really excited about it but i'm
also like
super nervous about it because it's a
it's a big
job like for us to get this studio
ready for that like it's it was never
made for that
right so like we're currently setting up
sets
effectively like locations like fixed
locations in the studio
wait what do you mean like sets of
locations like are you gonna transition
to oh this is
this is mike by the fireside kind of set
like pretty much
yes so we're going to have three three
locations in the studio like one
it's like a relaxed location one is a
behind the desk location and one
is a secret location that i won't reveal
just yet
okay because we're setting up something
which is in scope
maybe a little more than we should do
but if we are able to execute it and i
believe that we will
will be incredibly fun so it's a big
project and like i'm super happy that i
have
diana's time for this like she's
basically pushing everything to the side
to do this because there's no way i
could do this on my own
like even just like getting the basic
equipment that we need
is a huge task because like you try and
find a good light right now yeah i was
gonna say do you have
those uh those fancy like i don't know
what they're called the things that you
use to bounce the light off of so you
can look you know really great on yeah
i don't think i've gone to that level
what i mean the bounce shields i don't
know yeah
shields that's what they call it in the
biz uh you know like
this stuff like um and it's a great
product like
the elgato key light all the streamers
use these lights
they're fantastic i've been able to get
a couple of this more of your rgb
nonsense is that what you're talking
about here it's just a pure
light there's no rgb on this one but it
is it's something that all the game
streamers use
but yeah it's like this is an
interesting task to tackle
because this is not my world
uh so but it's something that we are
getting a handle
of during the fundraising process
between now and september 18th like
we're raising money all through
september but obviously we want to have
a like
a like a lead up to the podcast-a-thon
like we're going to be doing other
twitch streams
and this is all like testing of the
setups right okay
so we can make sure that like we have
the basics ready before we have to
commit eight hours you know
right yeah yeah that's not when you want
to find out how difficult it is to
switch between
sets is when you're trying to do
something live for eight hours exactly
like because
there's even like one thing where i've
already realized like oh okay
i found a great tripod i need two of
these
right and so like i've got this like car
we bought from ikea that has like a
small tripod on it
the laptop that i'm going to be using
the light and
gear right that i need in if i'm because
then basically we're moving this car
around to the different parts of the
studio right
so it's all in a fixed location but what
i've learned is for two of the locations
it would be better if i can just pop the
camera off and put it onto a tripod
which is on the ground rather than on
the car
so like this is the benefit of doing
these smaller tests
of trying to work out what this
environment
will be good for and there's like two
things which is like uh
benefits one i'm pleased we didn't have
this place entirely furnished because we
would not have the space to do what we
want to do
right right yeah you didn't know that
surprise you need to build
three filming sets in mega studio
and two it's helping us accelerate
the furnishing process because the stuff
that we need for this
so yeah it's this is a very interesting
task to undertake but i'm very excited
about it and it's
i couldn't find a better cause to do it
for so
cortex sense do us proud go to
studio.org
relay and donate now get ready for the
podcast-a-thon and i'll be talking about
it a little bit more next time
so as is usual for us i had like a
million more things that i wanted to
talk about today
right that we're gonna have to push to a
later episode because i was not
expecting
what was your quote mini topic in the
episode of reassessing your note-taking
to be an absolute fundamental rebuild of
what it takes to to make a note
yeah i'm sorry i didn't mean to totally
blow your plans like i thought that was
a nice
that might be a nice pre-show thing
look as i've said many times there's two
great things about
us having more like i have work already
done for next time
and two it gives us stuff to talk about
in more text
as well yes that's right but before we
go today
it's august and around these parts
august means
text adventures text adventure time and
we have another one so
on august 29th the upgrade
cortex crossover tax adventure for this
year will be published for relay fm
members
all relay fm members get access to this
so if you
are subscribed to more tax or you
subscribe to another show
there is a feed called relay of home
crossover which is where all of the
bonus content is posted
i'm gonna put a link in the show notes
so if you're a member and you don't have
the crossover feed you can just click
that and it will take you where you need
to go to sign up for it
but this is a great time if you're not a
relay firm member to try out more techs
because if you go to getmoretechs.com
you can sign up for five dollars a month
and you will get more tax and you will
also get the crossover feed that
includes the text adventure special
so you can give it a go and see what
you're missing out by not getting more
texts
there's gonna be a trailer at the end of
this episode so you can hear the
theme of this year's text adventure so
i'll play that for you
if you're not a member you need to
become one to get access to this go
to getmoretext.com you can sign up
you'll be able to get the more text feed
and the crossover feed that will include
the text adventure for you
and don't forget more text is longer ad
free episodes
of cortex so go check it out right now
getmoretax.com
mike gray welcome
to z ward
[Laughter]
here at the hospital entrance you're
outside the hospital where your sister
was admitted
nine weeks ago you may enter to the
north the hospital grounds continue
east okay i've already got to redo my
map okay wait a second
didn't last very long you read
the poorly spelled email you received
this morning
from your sister help zombie
apocalypse xoxo francis
looks like you're right mike it's zombie
time
the only real piece of information that
we need is what kind of zombies are we
dealing with here
are they like zombie zombies or are they
28 days later
zombies if they're zombie zombies zombie
zombies aren't that big of a problem
i'm hoping it's zombie zombies
you have a fire extinguisher if we have
to use this fire extinguisher to
extinguish a fire i'm going to be very
disappointed
it turns out this is just a lesson in
fire safety this whole adventure
i guess typical style we check this
floor right like let's not leave the
floor
mike you and i we're like we're like a
swat team here we're gonna cover our
corners
we're gonna take it floor by floor with
a fire extinguisher just like a good
swap team
the theater is filled with the shuffling
bodies of zombified patients and staff
members
there are too many zombies here to fight
upon seeing you they become agitated
and start to close in get out close the
door close the door
don't dead open inside reference
acknowledged
zombies begin to enter the kitchen we're
this round
we shouldn't have opened that door huh
the zombies attack you and bite you and
kill you and you die
the end all right okay
you open the heavy door and find a chef
say hello she says you didn't eat
anything did you the chief of staff told
me to add vitamin z to the meatloaf
after that everything just went to hell
no no i'm gonna turn the dial okay oh
but what i'm saying because
we need to do that right now you have no
sense of exploration mike
you guys may not remember the past text
adventures but we've had this
conversation before
set dial to high the machine hums and
the zombie thrashes around
but something goes wrong the machine
starts to smoke and the electrodes catch
fire
the zombie's eyes burst from their
sockets and the power goes out
are we in darkness i can't see anything
it's dark
i guess this is where we use the bullet
on ourselves and start over
or you could just you know load your
savings
[Laughter]
you managed to escape z-ward with your
life but you'll never forgive yourself
for the loss of your sister
the end boo okay
okay all right reload save stop too
i think it's the most judged we've been
by smellatron
[Laughter]
[Music]
if you want this text adventure it's
available for all relay fm members in
the crossover feed
you can become a member today at
com
[Music]
this is the world's most ambitious text
adventure crossover event that's not
that ambitious but still